Glory forever, Yorlisoning to ancient faithradio.com.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is never the...
haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints. In our time, many year into break
three of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see and to know reality as
it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it
well? How do we permeate every day life with spiritual presence? Orthodox
Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young,
host this live Colin show focused on
Enchantment in creation, the union of the scene and unseen as made by God and
experienced by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Hey good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers. Christ is risen. He truly is
risen. You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast. As you should be
doing, this is the only thing you should be doing right now. My co-host Father
Stephen D. Young is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana, and I'm Father
other end just even Damick in e-mail.
Pennsylvania and we are live and if you're you're listening to us live you can
call us at 85237-2346 and you can talk to us we're listening. We're going to
get your calls in the second half of the show and our very own Matyska
Trudy who assures me that her name is not a nickname we'll be taking your
calls. We have to we have to make a quick programming note here. Oh yeah so
So like people, I know people will hear this recording.
this is it directed to you but to those of you who have been listening to the
feed and who just spent the last hour listening to the commercial for Father
Andrew's new show. And now we're gonna have to listen to who knows upward of
three hours more of him. I know. Well here's an opportunity for you to apologize
to those people Father Andrew. I'm not even a little bit sorry. Okay, they could
turn their friggin' radio off. I also do have a technical
questions. I also had to listen to that commercial again. Oh, and may yet again before the show
is over. No, no, they're not going to play that one again. You said you said on this video
podcast, you're going to read the stories. Like are you going to have some kind of graphics
going on during that? Or are they just going to like sit there and watch you read? There
will be in fact some visual elements. Okay. Not just be us reading. Yeah. Because that's
That's a good thing to clarify for people.
Cause if you tell people, like, father see that,
you're gonna...
I'm gonna sit on YouTube and watch me put on my reading glasses and read for like 20 minutes like
That's not gonna sell it
Say there are people that would watch you do that
Maybe because they never know what I was gonna say right or do like you know make something. Yeah
Yeah, yeah, yeah, and you put your reading glasses on so dramatically, too
Yeah, well you have to put them on and take them off dramatically
I just did
That's part...
selling the whole thing. Anyway, for years, years, because this show is almost four years old,
you, the listener, have been waiting for us to do an episode or three on the book of Enoch.
Whether it's the 450-foot tall giants or the vagaries of the solar calendar,
we know you get excited pondering it and who wouldn't. But that's not what we're talking about tonight.
We are going to start a series on the Apaka.
Epocrypha.
It's a scary word for some folks suggesting secret esoteric weird tomes from the ancient
world.
Some say that the apocrypha are dangerous, full of forbidden knowledge.
So father, that's what they actually write.
Are, right?
Yes.
Yay!
That means I can't go home tonight.
Yeah, but actually no.
No, none of them were actually banned from the Bible.
Right. Despite what the history channel would tell you.
Suppressed by the Vatican.
Yes, none of them were taken and burned.
Yeah.
So,
yeah, apocrypha.
Well, we have to start by disambiguating.
So,
a lot of people, as I found out when I published a certain book,
a lot of people now, when they hear the word apocrypha,
think of the
old Testament books.
Right. The six or so old testament books like Macbede's and Tobit that are in the Roman Catholic
Old Testament and not in most Protestant Old Testaments. Right. And they call those books the
apocrypha. That is completely incorrect. That is a completely incorrect usage of the term.
Amen and share. So that is that is not what we're talking about when we use the word apocrypha.
we use it correctly.
The word apocryphal like the dictionary definition of the Greek word refers to something
usually you will see it translated as hidden or secret.
Because that makes it sound really fascinating and interesting, right? Like someone is hiding
this from you, someone is keeping the secret. But in actuality it's used to refer to private,
which you can tell is a related idea.
Right. Yeah.
Something you do in price.
it rather than in public is hidden or secret in a certain sense, right? Yeah. And so apocrypha
are works that fall into a sort of middle category throughout church history,
particularly in the east. That's why it's still a Greek word. There have been sort of three
categories of texts. There are books.
that are read publicly or books that are read in the churches.
Yeah, that's canon.
That's the Bible.
Yes, that's scriptures.
Right.
That category of scriptures.
There's, and then on the other end of the spectrum, there are books not to be read.
That's heretical stuff.
Right.
That's heretical nonsense.
And then in between, there is this middle category of apocrypha, of books that are to
be read in private.
Right.
And that distinction between public reading and private reading is kind of less intuitive now in our modern age because
because of literacy rates.
Right. I mean, most reading is private reading.
Yeah.
And so the difference between someone reading something at home or someone hearing it read in church seems less of a difference to us.
But until very, very recently, very, very recently, even in the quote unquote Western world, we
all couldn't do all that, but literacy rates were ridiculously low. So the example I like to give
on this is in World War One, World War One, if you are drafted into the US military to fight in World
or one. You were considered
considered literate if you could sign your name.
Right, rather than making an X, right, like a fixing your mark with a witness.
This is why they had to have notaries like people didn't have a signature.
They would just make it X and they'd have to have a witness there that saw them do it.
In case there was an issue later.
So being able to actually sign your name made you literate.
and
40% of the US Army was literate by that standard.
Okay, and so this is in the 19 teams.
This is like little over 100 years ago.
So for the vast majority of human history,
and still in very many parts of the world,
the literate people are the educated class,
which is a minority.
right in a given society. Why this is important in understanding this distinction is, something
that was read publicly was read to everyone. So anyone who was attending worship services
in the church would hear the text from the Old Testament, the Gospels, things.
from St. Paul's Epistles, the other New Testament Epistles, right?
These things were read publicly, which meant they were made available, they were read to
everyone. That doesn't mean everything in them was easy and clear to understand for everyone.
That's why there was, you know, preaching, right, sort of framed things and explain them,
but they were read publicly. They were put out there and made available to everyone. So,
then there are other tax, right, which for a variety of
reasons other than being purely heretical. Those purely heretical texts is like, nobody
should read that, there's nothing worth reading there. But there are other texts that had
valuable things to say that were related in some way to the Jewish or Christian traditions,
which had value to them, but also had other elements. So there might be things that were
erroneous in them. There might be things which could be very easily taken in a weird way.
Yeah, which is why sometimes like when this subject comes up, because I mean we've talked about
this before in the show, when the subject comes up, sometimes people ask things about a particular
book and say, is this book safe? You know because there's this idea that there's problematic bits,
But it's not like it's not like if you read some ancient text it's gonna cast some sort of weird spell
you. Right. Right. You know, the question is just do you have discernment and if something seems
weird to you, are you going to go off and do something weird or you're just going to go, oh,
that's weird. Yeah. You know, and move on. Yeah. And and this is by restricting that category of books
to being privately read, you're restricting them to a certain type of person being able to read them.
the literate basically. Right, the literate, which would be the educated classes,
which were usually like a Christian history, we're usually talking about clergy,
churchmen, other people of the educated classes, who would be equipped to read
them and sort of weed out the good and the bad, right, and those kind of things.
And so, for example, in the East in particular, the book of Revelation still kind
of hovers between the public.
and privately read categories.
Yeah.
Right, it's been affirmed as canonical,
but it's still not publicly read 99.9% of the time in places.
Certain very specific situations in places.
But outside of that, it's not really.
And you know, it's because I don't know
our listeners will believe this,
but some people when they hear stuff
from the book of Revelation go off on weird tangents with it.
What?
I know.
Hard-
do imagine, but true. My childhood has just been rewritten. Yeah. This by the way is also
what happened with origin. I'll get everybody worked up again. But when the only people
who were reading origin were people like St. Gregory, Ignissa, St. Basil the Great, St.
the failure of the agent in St. Jerome, right?
No one felt the need to condemn him.
because there were there were problems there but all the people who were equipped to read origin and
Could read that out. Yeah, just the nerds right they could take the good and drop the bat
Yeah, right
But as origin started being more widely read and quoted and as people showed up like methodius of Olympus who
Like went all in with some of the worst parts of origin
And publicly taught them that's when there arose a need in the church to condemn origin
Because this stuff was now getting thrown out to people who weren't equipped to deal with
it correctly.
And so the church responded by saying, you know what?
Don't read this stuff.
Yeah.
Because people are going off in weird soul-destroying directions with it.
Like thinking we're going to turn into spheres.
You don't want to be spherical but now...
religious. Yeah. They were kind of religious though. I mean I see what you're
trying to do there but it's that's when an originist doesn't go to church anymore.
Yeah yeah. So all that said right that sort of background. Tonight we're
actually going to be talking about one particular piece or one collection of
pieces I guess of apocryphal
text, apocryphal Jewish text from the second-table period, and that's the
testaments of the 12 patriarchs. Buckle in everybody, there's 12 of them. Yes,
12 patriarchs and 12 testaments, one for each. And this is for a bunch of
reasons. The reason why this is the first text that were
or we're devoting an episode to of the show
is that this is for a bunch of reasons,
I think the most important second-templed Jewish
or other apocryphal texts for Christians to get a handle on.
Yeah, and we should say that while the one that we're gonna,
the addition we're gonna be referring to,
probably the most is the Charles Worth collection,
which we recommend, and we don't get a kickback for this.
So it's usually the cheapest if you get the...
Charles with two volumes,
Suda Piggarafa,
usually cheapest at Christian book distributors.
Yeah, Christianbook.com.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
You can also read these texts,
another translation of these texts on the internet.
So if you just look up the testaments of the 12 patriarchs,
you can sit there and read them yourself.
So this is immediately available to everybody.
If you can hear this, you can look it up.
Yes, but if you buy actual paper books,
then the man can't steal your knowledge while you're...
That's true.
So, and mind as well just to say a few of those reasons, this is a text that gets, it's
a Jewish text, it's a pre-Christian Jewish text that gets preserved in orthodox monastic
settlements. It's an important link between
Jewish wisdom literature and Christian monastic literature, it's an important link in ideas in terms of how the New Testament
maybe especially St. Paul but also St. John interpret the Old Testament.
There's a whole bunch of reasons why this is probably the most important one.
And it's part of the Testaments of 12 Patriarchs are part of a broader genre of
of
Testaments that exist within second-touble Jewish literature.
This is Testament as in last will and
Testament. Yeah, since like a guy's final words before he
You know
Reposes like you know calls all the family together and says now listen up. This is what I have to say to everybody. Yeah
This is not Testament is in like Old Testament New Testament where that English word is being used to mean covenant
So these are not covenants.
by the or with the the 12 patriarchs. This is their last their last words to their descendants to
their immediate descendants and then from their their future and even distant future descendants.
And this genre follows the model of what we see in Genesis 48 and 49,
especially 49 but there's a little bit in 48 with Joseph's.
sons, where Jacob calls together his 12 sons and gives these sort of parting words, in
some cases parting shots, to his various sons.
And it's from what happens there in Genesis 49 that the genre really takes form because
What Jacob says to them is not...
their in Genesis 49 is not primarily directed to them as an individual
historical person. It's directed towards their descendants and more broadly to
the tribe that will later be named after them. Later in the Torah. So there is
this sort of prophetic element to what is said there. And that...
means that this genre because of that prophetic element, this genre becomes a way for
Jewish writers in the second temple period to sort of comment on then present events
but from like behind a veil a little bit. So rather than just saying, oh, here's my hot
take on the current Hasmodian King. Right. It's, you know, you frame it within...
the context of a biblical figure making a prophecy about the future that's talking about that
Hasmonian king. Right. Yeah. And I mean, we should say like this is this is very self-consciously
and very obviously pseudo-pigrafa, meaning that no one is actually claiming that these are from
from the men who there said to be from in the text.
This is understood to be basically.
a kind of fiction of sorts, you know.
Right, yeah.
Right.
And there's not even a full and fast one.
In these in particular, the test was the 12 patriarchs, there's not even a pretense
that the patriarchs themselves are writing it.
Yeah, yeah.
It's recorded as words that they are speaking before they die.
It never says who's writing it down.
Right.
Like, so there's not even a pretense that like of someone saying, oh, I was there and
wrote this down. Right. So there's not even sort of a fictional writer interpost.
But so yeah. And interestingly, so there are a couple places where the test of its 12 patriots
tap into sort of ennachic traditions that exist during the Second Temple period.
And the main way, there's another way, but the main way is that it will actually quote first
scenic.
We're going to be in it as quoted in two of the two of the testaments as what was written
by their forefather, Enic.
Now given within the frame of these are the 12 patriots, the 12 patriots by the way, just
to clarify for anybody who might have been clear to 12-
are the 12 sons of Jacob. Right. Right. Right. So in Genesis 49, we had the testament of Jacob
where he talked to them. These are presented as each of them when each of them died talking
to their descendants. Right. So of course there was no currently existing scripture
and existence at that time. These are people living within the pages of Genesis, the Torah.
hadn't been written yet and wouldn't be written for centuries. So the only thing they could
quote if you accepted that the book of Enic was written by actual Enic from Genesis would
be the book of Enic. That would be the only thing that was around at that time that they
could quote from. Otherwise it would be kind of anachronistic.
Right. So this does test it again. That's not like, oh, they're trying to cheat by only
According
from it, it more reflects the fact that it was broadly accepted in the second temple
period that Enic wrote the Book of Enic.
And for a long time thereafter, we've mentioned on the show before I know, Tertolian, for example,
completely believed that Enic had written every word of the Book of Enic.
more interestingly, St. Augustine, who rejected the teaching
of the Book of Enoch, still believed that Enoch had written something. He just thought that
the Book of Enoch had become corrupted. Right, so even he didn't throw the whole thing out,
despite not liking parts of it. He just said that the parts he didn't like were the corrupt parts.
But he believed that parts of this text went back to Enoch and had been on the ark.
Wow, preserved through the flood.
That...
at the beginning of the fifth century. Right? So, um, people firmly did believe that the book of
Enic went back to Enic, and that's that I think is more of what that reflects. Um, that an idea that
you know, oh, this is how we'll trick them, right? We'll make sure not to quote anything because
there are certainly plenty of illusions within these two things that happen in the Torah and things
that happen subsequently in the Hebrew Scriptures.
All the way...
up to the time of writing, right? They allude to those events all the time, right? So it's
not that they were, you know, exclusive of those things. It's just only the only quotes
are for me. So there's actually a pile of these. It's not just the testament of the 12
patriarchs. Testaments of 12 patriarchs are, I think, the most important ones. But there's
a testament of Adam, there's a testament of Abraham, there's a testament of Isaac, right?
like
A genre. Yeah, there's piles of these within Second Temple Jewish literature, and they all follow
this same frame of presenting the last words of whoever the biblical figure is with this prophetic
kind of import. And in the case of some but not all of them, but including at least a couple of
of the Testaments of the 12 Patriarchs,
that prophetic element also.
also forms an apocalyptic element, meaning there are apocalyptic journeys taken into the
heavens where things are revealed sort of from a divine perspective. Apocalyptic does
not mean about the end of the world. Apocalyptic means revelation meaning specifically that the
spiritual reality underlying historical events is revealed.
by someone being taken and given a heavenly perspective.
And so that's going to happen a couple of times in a couple of the testaments.
So we keep referring to them in the plural.
So the testaments of 12 patriarchs as a document has kind of a weird nature and history.
And I said there is a document and that's part of what causes the...
The issue with the kind of weird history is that it's very clear that at least some of
them circulated separately.
So we've got the testaments of the 12 patriarchs as we said that means we've got a testament
of Rubin, a testament of Simeon, a testament of Levi, a testament of Judah to write on down
the line.
And as I said, it's very clear that some of those circulated separately.
So we've got like separate copies of the testament of Levi and the testament of Nathalie, right?
With that aren't part of the collection.
Is there some kind of stylistic difference between them and the others?
No, not really.
Yeah.
So it's entirely possible that all 12 of these circulated separately.
On the other hand, some of them, the themes are so closely...
tied together from one to the next, that those particular ones circulate
separately would seem weird. It would seem a weird coincidence that they ended up
fitting together that well. And we don't have actual evidence like copies of
those that were separate. Right. So likely the most likely explanation.
I mean, we can't prove this, but the most likely explanation is that probably some of these
were composed independently and were separate testaments.
Because like we said, there's lots of these.
And then at some point, because these were brothers, these were the twelve brothers, someone
brought together the ones that already existed and then wrote the other ones.
Yeah, to make a set.
Yeah, to kind of produce a whole...
set as the testaments of the 12 patriarchs.
Right.
There's also a weird language issue in that there are clear
signs that in places throughout that they were written in Hebrew
originally.
But we only have tiny fragments of the Hebrew.
I'll see you later.
from the Dead Sea Scrolls.
So we don't have any Hebrew copies, whole copies of a single one.
We just have little fragments in Hebrew from different parts, enough to tell us that it
existed in Hebrew.
And there are things that in the Aramaic and Greek versions, which we do have whole
testaments in Aramaic and Old Testaments in Greek.
those show signs of being translation from Hebrew.
in places. Yeah. So you will get folks who say, well, these are originally written in Hebrew.
You can't really prove that because we don't have it, right? But it seems possible. But it seems
possible. And we know it was in Hebrew, but the other thing is
the aromatic and Greek have this weird relationship to each other. And when we start talking about
the particular ones, the particular test
will flesh this out. But so there's like Greek version and Aramaic version. And in some cases,
we have them, or at least have detailed notes on both versions. And the nature of both versions,
it is extremely unclear which one came first. So it's not as simple as like,
all that went from Hebrew to Aramaic to Greek, or even that it went from Aramaic to Greek.
There's just as much evidence that it went from Greek to Aramaic as vice versa.
And that being the case, that makes it very difficult to tell where the Hebrew fits in.
Like if it went from Aramaic to Greek, people would probably say, okay, well, it was part,
maybe it was like the book of Daniel in the Old Testament, that's in the canonical
Old Testament.
That was sort of part Hebrew and part Aramaic originally and then got translated into
Greek. Yeah, but we don't.
have enough of the Hebrew around to be able to make those comparisons.
Yeah, and there are other indicators that say parts of it could have been originally written in Greek.
Right. So we could have a situation where it's really nebulous. We could have a situation where,
for example, if it's true that some pre-existed and then it was compiled, that the pre-existing
pieces were in Aramaic and or Hebrew, and then it was collected and translated and filled out in Greek.
and then the new green
parts got translated back into Aramaic, right? There's there's we'll probably never know. Yeah.
They'll be very difficult for any individual text discovery to ever prove that one way or another.
So we've got copies from two different places. One place is the Dead Sea Scrolls at Comron where
where they were buried from the first century AD.
Now they aren't text from the first century AD necessarily.
They're mostly from the first and second centuries BC.
But they were buried there in the first century AD
when the Romans came through and recovered in the mid-20th century,
mid to late 20th century, and we've got copies from Mount Athos and St. Catharines.
Monasteries.
The earliest copy we have from Mount Athos is a Greek version
version from the
the 10th century, which is from Kutumusio, monastery.
And interestingly, while that text is all in Greek,
when you get to the Testament in Levi, he has these copious
note, margin notes about the Aramaic copy.
So however the monk was who copied it, could read Aramaic
and had the Aramaic copy there as well.
of notes all the different.
in the 10th century, in the 900s AD.
And sentry, Athernite textual critic.
Yeah, which means he was probably from Syria,
so it's a new air maq.
Yeah, yeah.
And so yeah, that's from the 10th century's the earliest copy.
There are other copies there from later.
But that's the earliest one.
We also, the earliest copy we have,
there are several copies at St. Catharines,
monastery, about Sinai, but the earliest one is from the 17th century.
And it's important to know that Christians preserve those texts.
Right?
Comoron was a Jewish community.
Yeah.
But the other place where we have this text are Orthodox Christian monasteries,
meaning rabbinic Judaism did not continue to keep and preserve and copy and hand down
the testaments of the 12 patriarchs.
but Christians did.
Yeah, the only reason we have these texts is because,
and it wasn't some random out of the way
weird village of Christians that did some strange thing.
I mean, Athos, Mount Sinai, I mean,
these are the most established central Orthodox,
you know, monastic communities.
Yeah, and St. Nicholas Forest,
the investor cuts.
that Noble mentions the testaments of the 12 Patriarchs.
Yeah.
In his list of books to be read privately in the ninth century.
So it was in the library Constantinople too.
So it's not just monastics.
Right.
Yeah.
It's also the imperial churches that were.
Yeah, and I mean, and this will probably become clear
as we go along tonight, but some people
might be asking themselves right now.
Well, if this stuff was being copied and preserved
used at such central places like the you know the
the the the patriarch of Constantinople and Manathas. Why have I never heard of this? And I would say that probably
Well number one, I mean, there's a huge amount of Orthodox literature that most people have never heard of
Yeah, right or literature that the Orthodox Church is preserved and kept whatever but also as you'll see a
Lot of what's really important for us about these texts is just fully absorbed into our tradition. Right
This is sort of a link in the chain of our...
of our tradition, right? So even if you never read any of these texts so much of what's in these texts made its way into the New Testament and then into
monastic literature and other forms of Orthodox literature and the fathers and this kind of thing, you get the content even without having read it.
Yeah, yeah, right so if you pick up this stuff and read it and you're and you know you've been formed in Orthodox Christianity
for a while probably very little will be surprising to you except for maybe the basic details of like the
story and stuff but the principles will all be very very familiar. Yeah. Maybe you might be surprised
that these principles are pre-Christian. Yes. I mean because they're pre-Christian. Yeah. Boys and
girls. But yeah, yeah, other than that, right, it's not going to be anything like weird, you know,
Nothing rewrites Christianity.
But it gives you sort of the link in the chain of provenance of the development of these ideas and these ideas being handed down.
So the sort of major themes that run through the 12 of them.
As I mentioned already, this is the form an important connector between Old Testament wisdom literature, Hebrew wisdom literature, and monastic literature.
You
Which helps explain why they were so important in Christian monastic settlements.
Lots of meditations on particular virtues, particular passions, or vices, right, particular sins, and forms of sinfulness.
The kind of thing that you're used to seeing in Orthodox monastic literature if you've read any of it, like Saint John Cash in Sinstitutes and Conferences.
Yeah.
And specifically the form that takes is that in many, not all, but most even of these
testaments, the individual patriarch is taken to be sort of an exemplar of some passion
or some virtue.
Yeah.
Which, you know, if you've ever been present for the chanting of the great canon of
St. Andrew of Creed in the first week of Lent or, you know, in the fifth week of Lent,
That form should be very familiar to you.
St Andrew Creed does-
exactly that kind of thing. The one probably the most memorable one from a particular translation
is when he's talking about Esau, you know, also called Edom, which means red, right? He says,
because it means a red hot, sin-loving soul. Yeah. Stick with that. Yeah. Yeah. So that mode of reading,
if you just recently in the last few weeks heard the great canon, will be familiar to you in particular.
And then of course as we mentioned there are apocalyptic visions of this future generation of the coming of the Messiah
that are the product of sort of the original context in which this was written.
Text was written by the way, I guess we didn't mention that.
The text of the whole, the whole thing put together, the collection.
We know existed from the first half of the second century BC,
so between 200 and 150 BC.
But it's important that none of it is sort of exegetical in the sense that it's like reading
and interpreting the book of Genesis or even later parts of the Hebrew Bible.
Yeah, which again would be weirdly inacredistic.
Right. And this is why it was sort of left behind by rabbinic Judaism.
Rabbinic Judaism chose to focus on the midrashim, the Tarrgameem, a kind of exegetical approach
of the Hebrew text.
going forward. And this is a very different mode of reading and interpreting
those scriptures that became the basis for a lot of Christian interpretation,
but obviously those interpretations went in different directions.
Yeah. All right. Well, I mean, this might be a shock to some of you. Only 39 minutes to know the show,
but we're going to go ahead and take our first break. So we'll be right back with the second half of Lord of the Spirits.
Father Andrews
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Ancient Faith Radio is brought to you by our listeners
with help from Byzantine coffee.
Enjoy a great cup of Byzantine coffee
while tithing to your parish.
In non-profit organization, Byzantine coffee is the product of prayer, reflection, and the
work of a few Orthodox Christians.
When purchasing our small family, co-op sourced and aerostened coffees, add your parish
discount code at checkout to type 10% of your purchase price.
We also offer a fine grind for your Greek or Arabic coffees.
Subscribe and save 5% on every purchase.
Visit us at Byzantinecoffee.com to learn more.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hi, everybody.
It's Lord of Spirits podcast.
We're talking apocrypha, specifically the testaments of the 12 patriarchs.
And you know, the thing that I kind of have...
on my mind as I was listening to that commercial is, you know, to the Byzantine Empire, yes,
yes, I know it's the Eastern Roman Empire, to the Byzantine Empire even have coffee. I think
it's anachronistic. I'm just throwing that out there. Look it up, kids. Let me know. A quick
googling suggests that what we now call Greek coffees, maybe only early 19th century.
But that doesn't mean you shouldn't.
by an agronistic coffee.
I'm okay with an agronistic coffee,
because coffee is coffee.
So yes, welcome back.
All right.
You have nothing to say about that father.
I was hoping for some kind of remark or...
Oh, maybe not.
The question is now, where has he gone?
Has he stepped out for a long, long,
Why does it smoke?
Yeah, no smoke breaks.
When I was a stage annual history for two
is checking for an eclipse, but we just had the eclipse.
So there's no more eclipses available.
So anyway, right.
That said, it does look like we actually
are getting a call coming in.
I don't know if Trudy's actually got this one piped through yet.
Who could it be?
Someone from Washington State?
Hello, do we have Anthony from Washington?
Yes, thank you.
Hey Anthony, welcome to Laura's Spirit's podcast.
I don't know if Father Stevens out, you know, taking a stroll around Lafayette, Louisiana
right now, but you're talking to me at least.
I was solving crime.
Yeah.
Well, thank you so much for this opportunity.
You're welcome.
Welcome to the podcast.
My question is about sabbatical years.
I'm running a company making Christian video games
and one of the big selling points I'm giving to employees
is the idea of the Sabbath year from Latura
and was finding or having a hard time finding any details
about whether or not Christianity still practiced
the practice of the sabbatical year.
And if so, if it was the same year
or a different year, or for any other differences.
I don't know. So I'm trying to figure out if you're planning to make this an employee policy.
Like okay, you get a year off. But the question is does everybody have to take a year off
all at once? Is that what you're saying?
Yeah, the goal is, as far as my reading and my interpretation would be to give everyone
the same year off all paid holiday for the year.
Wow.
I mean,
bless you if you've got the resources to do that that's amazing now everybody's
caught like wait what's this company everyone's gonna be applying for your
for your company now of course the you know the drawback is it's like what once
every 25 years or something right once every seven oh okay I'm thinking I was
merging with the Jubilee in my head I think that was that's that's the 50th year
oh the 50th year yeah so if you have any slaves Anthony you have to set them
free after that matter.
I mean, if you don't, then you don't have to worry about it.
Is that a thing, Father?
Like a whole year off?
Well, so I mean, technically, if you're talking about practicing it, Israel never practiced
it.
Yeah, they never happened.
Yeah, I'm familiar with that.
You mentioned that.
Yeah, yeah.
Jeremiah.
What's that out?
That they never actually did it.
So I don't know...
of a widespread Christian practice of doing it every seven.
Yeah.
It'd be hard to imagine how that would work.
Like if everybody took a year off,
like how would a society survive?
Well, the idea was you'd rely on God, right?
Like...
Okay.
But
And you left your, like you left your field for that year, but like the poor could come
and glean from the field during that year.
So, I mean, I do know there have been various points where there have been various sort
of Jubilee periods proclaimed by Christian, that involved the forgiveness of debts and
doing all those things.
But I don't know of any widespread practice.
Now that doesn't mean it would be wrong for you to do
with your own business, right?
Yeah.
That might be a very good thing to do.
Again, you would never lack for employees, I think.
And there's those commandments in the Torah
are laying out a system of economic justice.
Right.
Deuteronomy, it's particularly clear in the Greeks
is at one point.
there shall be no poor among you. And I get reminded of that every time I read
see we just read this last week in Holy Week, Christ saying to his disciples when
Judas is trying to fill up some more money, the poor you will always have with you.
That's really a stinging indictment. You know the Torah, right? Sort of the you
We will never live up to this.
Right.
But it seems to me if you're if you're gonna try to fashion
some concept of economic justice the place where you would go would be the scriptures and specifically the Torah and
Therefore aspiring to that I think would be a
Good thing. Yeah, I mean more power to you man
Do you have any suggestions about
timeline if I should just follow the Jewish year or it should be like seven years
my business or anything like that. I would I mean I would just do because it's
not sort of a culture-wide thing I would just do yeah based on years of your business.
Okay. There you go. All right well good money. Thanks for calling that's that's
That's what I've never heard before.
It's pretty great.
though. I hope that I hope that really works. I'm not saying I'm downing it whether it
will work. I mean, I really hope you can do that. That would be awesome. Yeah. So yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. All right. Well, I can see we've got another call coming in, but I don't
know if it's quite all the way through yet. Like this is these these emergent calls, you
know, that are just sort of on their way. This one is actually come. It looks like it's coming
from Florida or at least the first phone or through the astral plane. I'm getting something
Okay, now.
Yeah, I'm not a medium. So you're at least a lot. Yeah, I'm generally an extra large.
So all right. Do we have Florida there? Not yet. All right. Florida's in. Yeah, yeah, just
We're going to gamble Trudy, just let him through.
Okay, it's apparently John calling from Florida. So John, welcome to Lord of Spirits Podcasts.
We're glad to have you.
Hello. Can you hear me?
Yeah, we hear you.
Yeah.
Awesome.
The crisis is risen, first of all.
He truly is risen.
Yeah. So I had a question.
So at various points on your show, you've discussed it.
Nephilim and how when the Israelites would war against them, they were prohibited from taking anything that belonged to them.
But there are other contexts in which they were allowed to do so. So, you know, like plundering the Egyptians, for instance,
Is there a way to understand that to like apply it to our current lives?
That's my question. Thank you.
Wow. Well, I mean number one, probably you're not being asked to go to warfare against the Nephilim or
or hardly anyone. So the literal level would be hard to apply. I mean, I like there is this
this classic understanding of plundering the Egyptians, which is, I mean, this is an old
old idea, which is basically the idea of taking everything good from even pagan culture
and bringing it into the service of Christ, right? So like, that's why you get, for instance,
Byzantine era commentaries on the Iliad and the Odyssey.
Which I mean
those texts were written in totally pagan contexts.
And if you read them closely, are totally pagan.
And yet people like Steve Basel the Great
could look at them and say, okay,
there's some good stuff that we can take away here.
Not everything, but there's some good stuff
that we can take away here.
And so I mean, that is one of the classic ways
of quote unquote plundering the Egyptians.
Now, that's a metaphorical sense.
You know, we're not being called upon
to take anybody's stuff, like literally take their stuff.
You know, I mean, I have to remember that.
The people of Israel were functioning under direct commands from God to do certain things.
Like, it wasn't they were saying, how do we interpret this?
You know, it was go do this thing now.
I don't know, Father, you got any comments on any of that?
I think that sort of key to understanding that is that they were called upon to do something
that was wrong.
Like killing other humans is never good.
It's never good.
It is sometimes a necessary evil.
Right.
And so they're being called upon to commit this necessary evil.
And so not being allowed to take anything was part of God telling them like
you don't do this like to enrich yourself.
This isn't about you getting richer you getting slave.
Are you getting extra wives and concubines?
Right. This is this necessary thing that you have to do.
And no more.
And so, right, no more, and so you do it solemnly.
Right, you do it as a duty.
Right. Because
you know, the reason why everyone else in the history of humanity has gone to war has been
been doing rich themselves to gain power, to gain wealth.
Right? Literally everybody. Right? So
God is is kind of excluding that
Right as part of a way of teaching no this isn't good
You militarily dominating your neighbors is not a good thing
Right you seizing their riches and plundering them and making them your slaves is not a good thing
Right
It is something that occasionally because of the wickedness
of that group, right, becomes necessary. And so the way I would take that into our lives
is there are sometimes where there are things that we have to do that we take no delight
in in life. Right, there are sometimes in life where we're called upon to do hard things.
Make hard choices, right, do our duty. Even though it's objectionable or wrong, that
We wish it didn't have to be.
done. And the way when those times come, right, we should look at those not as
opportunities, right, to advance ourselves or enrich ourselves or to get something
over on someone else. We should not approach them with our own ego. We should
approach them as sort of grim and solemn duties. Then we have to perform
because it's the right thing to do.
All right.
In the next question there's a-
Yeah, that does pretty well. Thank you. All right. Thank you very much for calling. I mean
Nephilim are always on topic so yeah, absolutely. All right. Thank you
Okay, well that we've got 12 testaments to get through so where we can start
Well speaking of Nephilim, we're starting with a testament of Rubin.
All right, which talk is about them
Um, yes.
So that's not the main focus, but it comes up because yeah, yeah, because of what Ruben is most known for in Genesis.
So Ruben is the oldest brother, right? That's why we're starting with him. The testaments kind of go in birth order.
In terms of how they are arranged in the collection.
Ruben was the oldest brother. Ruben would have had the first born status to inherit
from Jacob probably.
Part of the tension in the story of Jacob and his sons is that, you know, Ruben is his first born son period, but he's the first born son from Leia.
Yeah.
And not the preferred wife.
Jacob is.
Yeah, Rachel's the preferred wife and Joseph is the first born of her. So that's part of the tension that goes on.
but he in normal circumstances would have inherited, he gets disinherited because of what happens in Genesis 35 verse 22.
which is he commits an act of family use or patient, which I think we've talked
about on the show before. Yeah we have. Yeah he sleeps with Jacob's concubine Bill Ha.
Right Bill Ha. One of his father's wives and he does this not only out of lust,
obviously, but he does this. The reason why and this happens several times in
Genesis happens later in the Hebrew Bible with Absalom and
David's lives. The reason for doing this is that this is a way that a son would try to
take control of the family from his father.
Because if you sort of control the fertility, then you control the future.
Right. And also, if you do this publicly, you sort of humiliate your father.
Yeah. Yeah. So, like, so in this, in this text, now this is not what's, in the scripture
does tell us he does this right?
Yes but...
But there's some details in this text that are sort of added.
And one of the, for instance, is that he waits until Bill Ha is drunk at a sleep and
he goes into her, he's the biblical language.
He goes into her and then leaves before she's even awake.
So it's clearly like, this is rape.
This is clearly him having a contact.
God text, yes.
Yeah.
is not a consenting partner right?
Yeah, yeah, consent to this time, but she's not a willing partner.
Right.
There's no sense in which she's deliberately involved.
But it's narrated that way because again, as we said, each of the brothers will represent
sort of a passion or a, or and or a virtue.
And Ruben is clearly lost.
And so he kind of gives a breakdown of the whole incident, which is aimed at very clearly
taking responsibility for it.
himself. Yeah, so this is repentant language on his. So he, yeah, he wants to make it clear. He
doesn't present it as, oh, she seduced him or did this or that, right? Or even was a willing
partner. This was all him, right? In his presentation of it. He talks about having, and there are clear
parallels to the story of David and Beth Shiva here that are, I'm sure, deliberate, where he sees her
bathing and that puts some thoughts in his head and then he's
sort of stalks her and then ends up, right, as Father Andrew said.
That makes sense with her while she's asleep.
And in the context of this also, this is why the Nephilim come up, right?
The Nephilim come up because there's sort of another example on the surface,
just another example of lust, gone awry, right?
But it's all
important than in both of these instances where we can't forget about the
family use or patient part. And we can't forget about with the Nephilim, the
King's part, in the sense that there's not just sort of lust in the sense of
sexuality, but lust for power also. Right, there's like a power dynamic
involved here. Right.
This isn't, we're going to see in a later testament,
this is going to talk about the importance of keeping sexuality
and reproduction together. Right? In this sexual act that Ruben commits,
there's no aspect of like procreation or anything like that.
This is purely a power issue. Right? That he's trying to take power
power from his father, likely in the context of Genesis because...
He didn't think he was actually going to get the firstborn status.
And so since he wouldn't have inherited that way, he decides to try to take over.
Yeah, the family.
But so another, some other added information that we get in this testimony of Rubin is that
he embarked on an actual period of repentance after he did this and after he was disinherited.
And it's...
I mean, this is really important to note because repentance, I think this is really, really, we have to say this a lot because I think a lot of people don't know how to repent.
Repentance is not just him saying, hey guys, I messed up. I'm really sorry. He has to, he does something. And in this case, he, he's fasting for seven years from, from meat and from wine.
Yeah, he eats no meat and drinks no wine for seven years.
And that's his repentance because he was, of course,
libeled to the death penalty for what he had done.
Yeah, that's what now there's no Torah yet.
But that's the principle within the scriptures, you know,
that you could, you could die for that.
So you don't have to die.
You can also repent.
Right.
You know, good news everybody.
He's took this concrete form.
Yeah.
Right.
A fasting for seven years.
Not just oops did a whoopsie.
Yeah, and and and notice that it worked out like I hoped it would.
And like the relationship between fasting from particularly from meat and from wine or all
called drink, like these are things that directly feed into lust if you eat too much of it and
drink too much of it. You know, like it's long known that these things are connected, right? So it's
not just, oh, here's this arbitrary thing I'm going to do because I'm sorry and want to prove that
that I'm sorry.
Like this is about reforming who he is as a human.
This changes who he is.
engages in this. Right. He had been chasing his appetites. And so now he
refrains from his appetites. Exactly. Yeah. And so and within the context of
that right that that understanding of appetites, there's this interesting
breakdown in the testament of Ruben of the seven parts of the human spirit, which
which doesn't... interesting...
doesn't does not match anything you really find in Greek philosophy. So this isn't a lot of times
people really want to give these like weird platonic and Greek philosophical readings to
second-tippled Jewish literature. And unless we're talking about phyllo of Alexandria, it doesn't
work out so well most of the time. So the seven parts of the spirit as they're laid out in the
Testament of Rubin. Part one, the most basic part is the soul. So he's making a
certain kind of distinction here between soul and spirit, the author, whoever the
author is, in that for him, the soul is part of the spirit. And the soul is here
very clearly the Jewish idea. It's the life of the body. Right. That's the first
part of the spirit. It's what makes your body alive. And then the next four
are sight hearing smell and taste, right, which are four of the five senses. Those
capacities, right? But then the sixth is the capacity for speech, which is part of
the human spirit, to be able to either frame words and communicate. But then the
seventh part, maybe waiting for touch, the other sense. This is the closest you
get to it. The seventh part is...
sex. And it's interesting, especially like there's no
gnostic sense of the spirit here. Like these are all
you know, these are mostly pretty bodily things. Yeah,
well, it begins with the soul that gives life to the body and
ends with sex for procreation. Yeah, yeah, this is this is
how the testament of Ruben defines the spirit. Right. And so
there is an idea here that gets developed further.
I
in the fathers and in Christian monastic literature, the idea of glameless passions,
the idea that they're appetites that are basic to being a human that are not innately sinful
when they're properly directed and indulged within proper limits.
Yeah, right. And so that's the take on sexuality here, right? Is that...
is this good thing, it's part of the human spirit, which means for the testament of
Rubin, it's part of the image of God.
But that it is good when it functions within the context of marriage and within the context
of procreation.
When it's divorced from that, then it can run into sinfulness very quickly.
So there
There's one particularly controversial bit about the Testament of Rubin.
It's not the bit about the Nephilim.
It's that in Testament of Rubin 51, and all this and all of the other numbers we're
going to give, the section in verse numbers that we're going to give, are from the Charles
Worth edition.
A lot of the public domain editions online do do things up differently and there's no
like standard.
Yeah, the verse.
is not the same everywhere because the verse of occasion isn't in the original.
Yeah. But so five verse one he says, women are evil.
Now I thought that was self-explanatory but Father Andrew said people might get set if we just
leave it at that. Might need to unpack that a little bit. Yeah. Yeah. So, you know.
So immediately like the
first thing, right, we jump to, and we hear that, is, oh, this guy's a misogynist.
He hates women.
Yeah.
Right.
But let's press pause.
Let's press pause.
Let's think back to like all the way to three minutes ago.
When we pointed out how when he presented his sexual sin, he presented it as completely
his fault and not the woman's fault at all.
Yeah.
So that's the context in which he then says this line.
Right.
talks about what
seducing and so forth. Right. And so he says, Bill, he already said, Bill
had did nothing wrong. Right. And but now he's saying this and he's talking about
women seducing men and leaving ministry and this. Right. So how do those things
even fit together? Right. Well, you have to understand in order to understand
speech, you have to understand the context into which speech is spoken. Right.
you have to understand the audience.
We talked about this back when he talked about how and how not to read the Bible, the idea of the ear,
recreating the ear of the first hearers.
And so, when you read this in context,
there was culturally and impression
That women did not have problems with loss.
Yeah, they were basically passive within this. That's how they were understood to be within
this culture that they're passive. Yeah. That that men had problems with lust, right? And
you can even even within the text of scripture, right? You look at Leviticus 18 and the laws
about sexual immorality, the commandments, they're all directed at men. Yeah, because again,
culturally in that time and place.
Men have
have the power in that way.
Right.
It made the choices.
Yeah.
Not saying that that's correct or how it should be.
But that's the way it was.
The way that it was.
Yeah.
That's the way there it was.
Right.
And so the dynamic, the sexual dynamic, as it was seen by average Jewish person in the
Second Century BC was men wanted to indulge themselves sexually.
right, pretty much all the time in any way they could.
And women were the sort of gatekeepers of chastity, right?
Women would sort of shut that down and keep it within its limits as best they could, right?
because they didn't particularly want to indulge themselves sexually.
Right. So what is being reflected here in the testament of Ruben in chapter five is Ruben is trying to explain
to his male descendants. Hey, guess what? In reality, women have problems with lust too.
Yeah, I mean in a kind of I
don't want to say backwards way. Sideways way. It's really saying that women have agency also.
Yes, women are-
innately good and pure and innocent all of them. Yeah. Yeah. Men and women both have problems with
this. And so that means since he's trying to talk to them, the whole frame of the testament of
Ruben is don't do what I did. Right. Don't give into lust like I did. Right. Don't hand yourself over
to lust like I did. And so what he's saying here is you can't just blanket trust.
women to help you do that. Right. You're going to have to conquer this yourself, dude. Right.
There are women out there who will be more than happy, right? To engage in all kinds of sexual
immorality with you. You can find them. Okay. So you can't count on them. They're shot this down.
Right. He doesn't say women are evil and men are good. He says women are evil also. Yeah,
Yeah, that's for the way it was.
And therefore a man has to exercise self-control.
A man has to keep himself to the commandments of God.
Right. And the form this takes culturally then.
And as you find this all over like Proverbs all over the Hebrew Bible and Jewish wisdom literature.
But reflected here to the testimony of Ruben is you find love, you find happiness with the wife of your youth.
Yeah, the woman you married when you were young.
When you're
13 and you were married off to some woman you might have never met before. Yeah.
Right. Her. And now you're however many years old and neither you nor she
are in the shape you were in back in the day. Right. That's still the one. Yeah. And so you find love
and you find happiness with her. Right. And you don't go outside looking for sexual gratification.
And you don't try to use sexuality for power.
You don't do any of those things.
Right?
You find happiness with her because that's the proper place.
Yeah.
Or sexuality, which is part of who you are as a human being, but this is the place for it.
That's the overall, right, theme.
So who's up next?
in general when you're reading A.C.E.L. literature.
you can't be easily triggered.
Or you eat something like winter or you go,
or like assume that,
you gotta as much as you can try to set aside
your modern assumptions about stuff.
So even if you are gonna evaluate a text
from a modern point of view,
at least try to understand what it's saying first
by setting aside your modern point of view for a few minutes.
Right.
Yeah.
And then it may be saying something that's objectionable.
Yeah, it might.
Right.
I mean, you read Aristotle about some people who are just fit by nature to be enslaved
and you ultimately say, no, I think he was wrong on that one.
Yeah.
We've gotten better.
Right.
But first you have to understand what he's saying and what he means.
Before you do that.
Yep.
Okay.
We got 11 more brothers to go.
Yep.
So who's next?
Next is a testament of simian.
All right.
So it may be the second board.
So, Simeon is the first one that goes
to a particular place.
So you may be thinking if you're tracking with this,
you may be like, okay, well,
yeah, so like Ruben did this thing
and you know, there's Judah did some stuff
and leave out some stuff and Joseph,
there's lots of stuff.
You may be wondering like,
what about like, Asher?
You know, or Issacar, right?
Some of these guys who there's very little
about.
like in the actual book of Genesis,
where are they gonna go?
Most of the time, as we read through these,
if there's not an obvious place to go
in the book of Genesis about that particular brother,
that particular patriarch,
they're gonna go to the episode
where they sold Joseph a slavery.
Right, yeah.
The main function of these guys
is what is their relationship to Joseph?
Yeah.
Right. So where they were.
Some of them at least were wanting to kill him they end up selling him into slavery
Right, so if we've got nowhere else to go with a particular brother
We're mostly gonna end up going there, but we're gonna see even that one event
being looked at from a number of different angles
Because of that and the sort of particular angle
with Simeon in his testament is that
he wanted the reason he wanted to kill him.
Joseph and this murderer is intent toward him was out of envy. So envy or jealousy is sort of the
passion, right, that that simmian sort of embodies. Yeah, so it's envy for the way that Jacob loved
Joseph best, but also frankly that Joseph is awesome. Yeah. In the testament of simmian, it's even like
Joseph was better looking than Sim...
Joseph was just like everything about, he's just like a full on-hater, like everything
about Joseph was appeared to him. And then it boils down to, but it's boiled down and very
deliberately to ultimately that Joseph was good. Yeah. And that simian as a person who was not
not always so good.
Right.
the fact that this person who was so good was around him called him.
And there are deliberate shades of Cane and Abel here. And even of,
you know, frankly, the devil and Adam, right? You know, there's the sense that the evil one,
you know, a Flixman kind out of envy. Right. Right. And that Cane and Abel interpretation,
by the way. This is one of the places where some of this surfaces in
in the Johanian literature, in first John, right,
when St. John says why Kane killed Abel,
ultimately it's because Abel's works were good
in Kane's removal.
And Kane couldn't stand it.
Right, that just brought this hate out of him.
Yeah.
Another interesting sort of interpretation here
is that
The whole story when it was a long it goes for a couple chapters in Genesis when the
brothers finally come to Egypt during the famine to get food.
And they're talking to Joseph and don't realize it's Joseph because he looks like an Egyptian
now and they thought he was dead.
He sends them back and forth and he hides the cup and you stole all the stuff he does.
There could be read in a number of ways, right?
You can read it as just trolling.
You read it as a bunch of other things.
But the way it's read in the testament of Simeon is Simeon sees it as sort of a penance.
Right.
Simeon sees having gone through all that as sort of a corrective to that jealousy and envy
here because
Because if you read it closely in Genesis, the way Joseph set it up, the whole thing was
set up to see how his brothers looked at had been treating viewed Benjamin.
Because Joseph knew that with him gone, Benjamin was going to be the favorite.
Jacob was gonna be doting on him maybe even more so because he's now the
only son of Rachel. And he reckoned that that would cause similar problems with the other
brothers. And so if you read what Joseph does, the reason he hides the cup in Benjamin's
stuff and everything, and he says, oh, I'm going to keep Benjamin here. Right? Like,
as you know, while you go get your father this, and they're freaking out, right? Is he's
kind of making them all...
display what he hoped would happen, their love and concern for Benjamin, their
brother, even though they were jealous. Right. And so within the testament of
Simeon, Simeon got that message in the sense that him working through his
willingness to do whatever he had to do to save and protect Benjamin.
taught him and showed him and transformed him from the envy that had become murderous in the case of Joseph.
So it's kind of an interesting and deep meditation on the Scripture there.
That's not what I would call exegesis but it's an understanding derived from that again of repentance.
Repentance as transformation and particularly transformation.
of the passion that was afflicting him, right?
Of the sin that had taken control of him.
The testament of Simeon is also where we find
our first prophetic piece that seems very clearly messianic.
Yeah, this is so cool and kind of unexpected
unless you know, know that you should be looking
this kind of thing.
So this is from the, again, this is the Charles Worth first vacation, chapter 6, verses 5 through 7.
It says this, then Shem will be glorified, because God the Lord, who is great in Israel, will appear upon earth as a man.
By himself he will save Adam, then all the spirits of error will be handed over to be trampled upon,
and men will have command over evil spirits. Then will I arise in gladness and I will bless
the most high for his wonders, because God has taken a body to eat with human beings
and to save human beings. Remember this is BC, folks. This is BC.
Yes, now of course, right. Some scholars.
Those most influenced by our 19th century German friends, are you just de facto? Oh, this
was added.
by Christians. Yeah. Right. Why? Because it's two on the nose. Right. It's two on
the nose. This has to be sort of a Christian thing. But you know, given that they have no
actual evidence or basis for that, right? Right. Let's pause and think about it a little
bit. Okay.
Look at, say, Baruch.
Right?
The book of Baruch, which is one of the books that's in the Orthodox and Roman Catholic
Old Testament.
It's not the Protestant Old Testament, but, incontrovertibly, a pre-Christian Jewish book.
Right?
Jewish text.
says in it, God has appeared upon earth and dwelt among men.
Now of course, Christians take that and interpret it crystallologically.
It says Christians reading this would take it into a crystallologically.
But that doesn't mean it's a Christian interpolation.
It doesn't mean it's a post-Christian text.
Just because it's read that way.
And you know, you don't even get out of the book of Genesis before you see...
God taking a body and eating with human beings. Right. Right. And it happens again in Exodus.
Right. And if this is a Christian interpolation,
why the exorcism stuff? Hmm, trampling upon spirits and so forth. And then we'll have command over
evil spirit. Yeah. Like this is.
big time second-teple Jewish stuff, exorcism stuff, right? But like second, third century AD
Christian literature, how much of that do you see? Answer not tons. Yeah, so this is completely
of a piece with pre-Christian literature. There's stuff like this all over pre-Christian Jewish literature.
This is the stuff the Christians picked up on.
Yeah, absolutely.
And I mean, it would make sense also why rabbinic Judaism was kind of like not interested in reading this stuff anymore.
Yeah.
But that doesn't mean, right, that doesn't mean, um, that it's somehow has to be, it has to be post-Christians.
Right.
The early Christians from the Apostles on.
Right. We're reading the Hebrew Scriptures and other Jewish literature. That's where they
developed their religious understanding from. They were Jewish. Right. But there were things
that they found there that they were applying to Jesus of Nazareth as the Messiah that shaped
their understanding of Jesus of Nazareth as the Messiah that were actually there before Jesus
was born. Yeah. That's how that works.
Right. Yeah, so we're going to see I'll I'm
Belaboring it now. I'm going to
Belabor it less. There's going to be more
Examples of this. Yes.
I'll Belabor it less than not zero but less.
And this is probably one of the reasons
why this is a good like intro text if
you're going to start reading some of
These apocrypha
You know because a Christian will see
All kinds of linkages.
Yeah, if you're going to go around and
Yank out everything that sounds Christian
and you're gonna have to get...
really half the Hebrew Bible. True facts. Like it doesn't make sense. Okay. Don't
don't. Anyway, yeah, testament of Simeon. All right. So who's next? The suffice for the
testament. So the testament of Levi. Next up, this is one of the ones that we
no circulated independently because we have that Comeron, for example, a separate copy.
of it, like just by itself without the collection. Just here's the testament of Levi.
So this is when we know was originally a separate independent document.
Further testimony to that is this is the text that we have at the copy at Mount Athos.
as we mentioned in the first half that is
In Greek, but the copious had the Aramaic version.
Okay. Yeah. And annotated the Greek version.
Put in margin notes, all the places where the Aramaic version was different, or a little different, or could be read differently.
So we have an incredibly high level of detail in terms of the text of this one.
And it's also it's also important to
note in terms of the whole collection because we're just talking about stuff that seems
kind of on the nose Christian, right?
There's also elements of this, like one of the main elements of the whole text that really
gets brought out starting with the testament of Levi that was completely abandoned by Christianity.
Right, we'll talk about that in a minute.
So it's not that this whole text reads like a Christian text.
There's a reason why this is in the apocrypha category.
This is a conglomeration of a whole bunch of second-devil Jewish traditions, some of which
are part of the inheritance of Christianity and some of which Christianity left behind.
Yeah, stuff gets sifted.
Right. This isn't Scripture.
But so Levi, as you might expect, the Levi's are the priesthood.
Aaron is the Levi Moses is the Levi.
and the Levites at all assist the priests.
So you might imagine the testament of Levi,
what if something to do with the priesthood,
there's a problem there, though,
in that Levi himself, right,
like the person Levi, the son of Jacob, in Genesis.
Not really a priest in any special sense.
Yeah.
in his household he was a priest.
in the extended family sure, all those priestly roles. Yeah, but he wasn't a priest in a special sense
that his brothers weren't. Levi was not a little bit a little bit a priest.
Right, so all that happens later in the Torah. Right, we've talked about that on the show.
With Aaron and Vinyus and the Levites at the episode of the Golden Calf, where the priesthood
is kind of taken away from the other tribes and given to them in a special way.
and happen with Levi. And so the information we have in Genesis about Levi is sort of recast
the testament of Levi to kind of make him one. Yeah. To kind of make him the archetypal sort of
priest. And so the way that that's done is what we have in Genesis about Levi, probably the most
notable thing that Levi the person does in Genesis is leading the
MASSIC
of all the men of Shekham.
Yeah, to prevent intermarriage with...
Well, not in Genesis. Sorry, sorry, sorry.
In this text, that's what it is.
Yeah, so it gets changed a little, right?
I'm getting it mixed up now.
Yeah. So in the text of Genesis,
the sister of these 12 brothers, Dina,
is sexually attacked by the men of...
the city of Shackham. And the village of Shackham, I should say. And the brothers want revenge
for what was done to their sister. And so Levi leads them and going to talk to them and convincing
them all to get circumcised. And while they're recovering from having been circumcised,
He leads the brothers, they go through, they massacre all the men of the town.
Wow, well, they're trying to recover.
And then Jacob, of course, gets very angry because he's like,
word of this is going to get around it.
People will come after us, right?
Like you've started this cycle over Venge.
Right? This is seen as a bad thing.
Yeah, yeah.
In the text of Genesis.
Okay, but now testament of Levi, we have a goal.
We want to make Levi the archetypal priest.
And so this whole incident gets sort of recast in a different way.
Okay.
And so we have this massacre at Shackham, and we have an author who is familiar with the rest of the Torah and the rest of the Hebrew Scriptures who says, well, you know what?
There's a whole bunch of people, later on in the Hebrews' riftures, who received the priesthood
based on killing a lot of people.
Right.
To stop incidents of like idolatry and sexual immorality and that kind of thing.
Yeah.
They take this kind of violent action and are rewarded with the priesthood.
So right, let's massage this a little.
And so in the testament of Levi, it is not that dying to get sort of sexually assaulted.
that Jacob is going to marry...
Dina to a cana knight. Yeah, which would make her the wife of an idolater from this family. Right. Yeah. And yes. And so Levi and there's a right to think that this is horrible.
Jacob is in the wrong. And so Levi goes and gets a circus
the massacres of the wall in order to sort of restore justice.
and correct this and prevent that inner marriage from taking place. Right? So that's an interesting
sort of massage that doesn't entirely work. Right. But then in the testament of Levi, we kind of
quickly move past that too. Now Levi's reward, he makes this sort of mystical apocalyptic ascent
into heaven. Right. And once he's been brought up.
into the heavens, he is vested with the high priest's
vestiments, even though those aren't going to be made until
later in the book of Exodus, long after he's dead.
But that is done in that way because this text is attempting to
present the Levitical priesthood as eternal.
Yeah. And therefore, including Levi as the fountainhead of
that priesthood. Right. Right. Levi is the sort of eternal
archetype of the priesthood.
And so we've talked before when we talked about Messiah's that there were a number of
Jewish groups looking for more than one Messiah.
Right.
The test of it, the 12 patriarchs is one of those texts that talks about two.
One of them is a priestly Messiah.
And then we're going to see in the next Testament a kingly, Davidic Messiah.
the Messiah were more used to talking about and thinking about.
But the priestly Messiah here is explicitly going to restore the Levitical priesthood, which
is seen as eternal.
So this is one current in second-table Judaism.
Yeah.
And again, this is one of these things that as Christians, we look at and see, okay,
well, that's not quite right.
Yeah, there's their own Messiah who has both these
It's not the little bit of a priesthood. It's his own pre you know like that's why you sort of sifties things
That's why it's not scripture, you know, yeah, there are other currents like we've talked about before in the Melchizedek episode
Right and we'll talk about more as we talk about some of these texts
There's also this current that sees the priesthood of Melchizedek
Psalm 110 right as the paradigm for a new priesthood in the new covenant
So it's not a restaurant.
of the Levitical priesthood, it's the Levitical priesthood is superseded by this other priesthood.
And Christianity, see the book of Hebrews, picks up that other current.
Right. It says this is correct.
But so this has this idea of this priestly Messiah and the restoration of the Levitical priesthood.
What everybody agrees about is that by like the first century BC, the first century AD,
the Levitical Presid was a mess, and it disrepair the Sadduce's stunk.
They wouldn't accept the Sadduzies.
It was not that page, but what the solution was going to be there were different ideas.
So the test of the Levi also directly quotes Firsteenek for the first time,
says Enek our forefather said, it's quote from Firsteenek.
But another important distinction, and this is going to carry through for the whole rest of the testaments of the 12 Patriarchs,
is that not
only are they they're these two figures. The priestly Messiah and the royal or
King Lee Messiah as two figures, but the priestly Messiah in the testimony of the
12 patriarchs is the one that's on top is the most important one. So if what we see
in the Hebrew Scriptures is that we see king and high priest.
more in, this is anachronistic, but more in the Byzantine mold of emperor and patriarch,
right? The idea that there's this kind of symphony, right? There's these two spheres.
Yeah. Right? There's sort of a civil sphere over which the king is in charge and there's a sacrificial sphere
of worship over which the high priest is in charge, right? In terms of what we see in the Hebrew Bible,
revival in the old car.
this is arguing that in the restoration of all this, when the Messiah is in this case come,
that the priesthood is going to be elevated above the kingship, that that relationship is going to change.
Now again, the Christian tradition picked up the stream that they're going to be merged.
in the figure of the Messiah.
Again, see Hebrews.
But this is a different kind of anticipation, right,
where the priesthood is going to be elevated over it.
And so that is likely picking up on sort
of the ambivalence about kingship in first Samuel
and that kind of thing, right?
The idea being that, well, clearly based on Judaism,
based on the Torah, there was going to be a king,
Bye.
But maybe the problem was that it should have stayed kind of a theocracy with the King as
a player in it, right?
This is sort of early Jewish political theory in terms of what we would call the relationship
between church and state.
But reflects one of the primary things that second-tabled Jewish groups were reflecting on was
what went wrong.
And why did it go wrong?
It's very clear that he revival, the Old Testament, is the story of things going wrong.
Yes, it is not the tale of a glorious civilization and its glorious leaders.
Like, this is not a pagan story.
Right.
And so they were anticipating the restoration being permanent.
Right, part of it being a true restoration would be
it's not going to all fall apart again.
And so you find a lot of ideas being cast in terms of,
well, how is this going to be different than the last time
so that this doesn't all repeat itself?
Right? This cycle doesn't just repeat.
And so test-reviewed by advances one possible answer
that didn't end up being correct.
Um
There may be I don't know there may be some groups out there in rabbinic Judaism who have something similar to this who think there's gonna be a restoration of the priesthood and
That it's gonna be that it was gonna take power over the civil government. I don't know but
If you're part of such a group call in now
And let us know yeah, yeah no fakes
So then next up
Fourth Brother, testament of...
Judah. And so this is now we're going to talk about the Messiah we're more familiar with,
right? Because Judah is the tribe that David comes from. That's right. I mean, this is one where
where Jacob in his in the biblical testament of Jacob, you know, he says the scepter will not depart
from Judah. Right. Right. Yeah. Right. Talks about him tying up his cult next to a vine and
his milky teeth and
bloody wine and all that stuff. I mean we just heard this like two weeks ago
Saturday. Yeah. But yeah, so this is sort of our thing. We have a slight
similar issue to what we had with Levi in that Judah himself the person, the
son of Jacob. Was it really the king of anything?
Yeah.
So again, you got to cut out projected backwards on him.
And so which Jacob, you know, kind of gives us the key to do anyway, right?
He says that, right?
So right about the decisions.
But also the thing with Judah is, um, you also can't sort of do what you did with Levi.
The sense that you can't have him being taken up into heaven and being made the archetypal
king, because it doesn't really work the same way.
Um, yeah.
So we've got to come at this in a little different direction.
And the way to do that is we just portrayed Judah as like the ultimate warrior, right?
Right.
Yeah, because that's what a king is back in the day.
He's the one who goes in and comes, you know, goes out and comes in as it says in the
Bible.
Yeah.
So he just get the daring exploits, right?
And a lot of these daring exploits are kind of stolen from other figures of the Hebrew
Bible, right?
like he rips a lion in half with his bare hands.
We need to pizza. He goes and he kills a giant by throwing a rock at it.
You're kind of like, where do I read that somewhere else? So there's a lot of that kind of thing.
We get all these exploits of Judah going out and kicking butt and taking names.
But we also have this stuff.
though from Genesis about Judah, like the whole Judah and Tamar thing, and the fact
that Judah himself married a foreign wife, which we just established with the Levi thing
is very bad.
Right.
So we've got to mesh these two things together, right?
How do you mesh that together?
We've already portrayed Judah as being hard-liven.
So now we just also haven't been hard drinking.
Drink hard play hard.
Yeah.
So the testament of Judah takes the perspective that all that bad stuff that Judah did.
He did that while he was drunk.
Hmm.
He did too much partying.
Yeah, which then sets up this question of being ruled by, you know, a bad spirit.
Punful.
Right.
Intended.
So he...
He takes the passions as being spirits,
as being unclean spirits very literally.
Yes.
And it talking to his ascended,
he says, you could be led by the spirit of God
or you could be led by these other spirits.
Right.
Right of the passions.
And spirits that come in a bottle,
related usage.
But so, at this, right, reflects.
his descendants in a particular way, right?
Because what did David go wrong?
Women.
Yeah, yeah, right?
Started multiplying wise.
Where did Solomon go wrong?
Also women.
Same place, right?
So he's speaking to his descendant saying, look, you know,
I'm this awesome dude doing all this awesome stuff,
But...
You've got to you've got to still exercise self-control
right and
Alcatal alcohol here drunkenness
becomes sort of the
Label or heading under which all forms of self-control
Right
They place it. It's kind of an appropriate one because you know as
You become drunk you lose your inhibitions
Right. They knew that back then. They saw it happen. Right. So even if you are a relatively
self-controlled person, drunkenness is going to erode that self-control.
So within the test of Judah, again, we get an idea of when everything is restored, when
everything is fixed with the masayas, the multiple masayas.
come that the tribes are going to be put back in order. Israel is going to be put back together and put back in order.
And when it's put back in order, there's going to be an order of the tribes, like an order of inheritance among the sons.
But it's not birth order.
Yeah, it's a different precedence, order of precedence.
Right, and as we mentioned in the testament of Levi, Levi becomes number one.
Levi is becomes the first tribe, becomes the one in charge.
Then Judah, who you have the Messianic King coming from, then interestingly Joseph, meaning
particularly Ephraim, Ephraim being the tribe from which most of the kings of the northern
kingdom came.
The capital, Samaria wasn't all that.
And maybe he's reminding.
Yeah.
Okay, go ahead.
I was just saying, just to remind everybody, in case you're like, wait, tribe of Joseph,
tribe of Joseph, that's because there's these as scripture calls on the two half tribes,
you know, Ephraim and Manasseh. Right. And Ephraim is the main one.
In Genesis 48, Ephraim is treated as his firstborn. And was the largest of the 12 tribes.
Well, I was going to say, you know, you may be thinking, uh, wait a minute,
they don't exist anymore. At the time, this is being written. Yeah.
Put a pin in that.
Put a pen in that. We'll come back to that in later testaments. And then fourth is Benjamin.
The other son of Rachel, but also Benjamin remember what tribes actually were still around when
this was being written. Yeah, basically Judah Benjamin. Levi Judah Benjamin. Yeah.
Because Benjamin stayed loyal to Judah and didn't join the Northern Kingdom.
them. But then there's there's Joseph in there.
come back to. Yeah, and so we see here reflected again the idea that there's these two
sides one priestly and one kinglay. So number five, the testament of Issaqar. Issaqar. Coolest name
in my opinion of the 12 brothers. He's a failed to deliver. I know there's not a
actual content of Bible.
Yeah, so Issa Carr, there's not much about in Genesis, but there is actually something about
the circumstances of his conception.
And so that's where this testament goes.
We probably should have put a parental advisory at the beginning of this episode.
Oh, well.
Too late now.
Yeah, so...
In Genesis, again a story in Genesis.
A lot of these stories of Genesis we've been talking about tonight are not the ones they
based your Sunday school lessons on when you were seven.
For obvious reasons.
Indeed.
No.
So there is this episode in Genesis that's recounted where Leah has a bunch of
mandrakes. Lay the wife of Jacob and Rachel the other wife of
Jacob, her sister, want some of the mandrakes. Leia agrees to give Rachel some of the
mandrakes. If Rachel will give up one of her turns sleeping with Jacob. Yeah, just a lot
of layers there. Yeah. So this is a this is an odd story. Now the mandrakes, the whole
issue of the mandrakes is that
they believed at the time that I don't know maybe it's true if you're a doctor or an herbalist
call in but they believed at the time that mandrakes aided with female fertility.
So the idea here is that Rachel remember was having trouble conceiving children.
Leia already had a bunch of sons, a bunch of kids with Jacob.
Rachel was having trouble conceiving. She wanted to conceive. That's why she...
wants the mandrakes. Right? To help her get pregnant, so she can have babies. And so Leia
exchanging those to Rachel in order to sleep extra with Jacob is interpreted by the testament
of Issa-Car as Leia wanting to sleep with Jacob for pleasure.
rather than procreation, whereas Rachel was focused on procreation, on having a baby.
And within this, Rachel is seen to be the one who is choosing the better path.
So the idea here is about marital chastity.
we would now call marital chastity, meaning which does not mean celibacy within marriage.
There is no form of Judaism, past or present, and probably future that saw celibacy within
marriage as a good.
Yeah, yeah.
The New Testament, which was written by a bunch of Jewish people, does not see celibacy within marriage as a good.
I will leave it at that because we have Roman Catholic friends listening.
And some other friends, too.
But chastity within marriage is a different thing.
Yeah, right.
Yeah.
Uh, chat...
within marriage has to do with the way in which sexual desire functions between a
married couple. And sorry, St. Augustine. As St. Paul said, the marriage bet is
totally un-defiled.
Not all-
all sexual expression, especially within marriage, right, between a husband and a wife, is
tainted by lust. It simply isn't, right? But the sin of lust can certainly happen within
in between a married couple.
Yeah, yeah.
Right.
And the key...
as the testament of Isocar sees it. The key to maintaining
chastity within marriage, with the marriage when remaining
holy in undefiled, is that sexual expression always remained
coupled with the idea of procreation. The idea of bringing
new life in the world.
Not that it happens every single time, right?
Or should happen every single time, etc., etc.
There are multiple purposes to sexual expression within marriage, but whenever procreation
is excluded from the picture, things go to bad places very quickly.
Yeah, right.
Whatever that's room
moved. Beyond that, so that all had to do with the circumstances of Issaqar's conception,
right? So that's here. Issaqar, you know, I find it odd that a dying man wanted to tell
his sons about how he was conceived by their grandparents, but hey, that's what happens here.
Yeah, that's...
And but then beyond that about him as a person, he is sort of he's presented as a farmer.
Yeah, he devoted his life to farming. And so there's an expression here of sort of a
gerarianism, the life of the farmer, working the ground, bringing forth food to provide for
himself and his family as virtuous, right, the sort of virtue of his labor.
Yeah, and I mean kind of it is more like a sleep,
analogously linked to the whole fertility
procreation thing.
Right, right.
To present this overall picture of,
so this is sort of we had the negative picture,
right, of years where things went wrong,
find love with the wife of your youth.
This is more a picture of what that looks like in a positive sense.
Right.
Yeah.
You marry,
You have kids.
you work hard, support yourself and your family, right?
He sort of, as St. Paul would later put it in terms of what we should aspire to,
he lived a quiet and peaceful life,
right, in godliness and sanctity.
And the text of the test of the Visccar really wants to
point out that sort of that life that Isocar led
is just as heroic and just as noble as Judah with all his exploits.
Right, and all the excitement, all the action and adventure going on over there.
Right.
This quiet life that Isocar leads is just as noble and heroic as that.
Sort of a central concern.
So that number six.
All right.
To round out second half.
Also, the next town in North Carolina.
The number six?
Yes.
Well, not number six, but the content of number six.
So
Okay, okay, Zebulin.
Oh, okay, the test of it was Zebulin.
Okay.
That would be cool if there's a tab called number six.
I'm from number six North Carolina.
Everybody be on what?
Yeah.
No, yeah.
Zebulin, it's near, it's near Raleigh.
It's on the east side of Raleigh.
Yeah.
So,
Zebulin presents himself interestingly.
Right at the beginning is only having committed sins of thought and sins of ignorance in his whole life
Hmm, so he's dying and talking to his sons and
That may just sound weird, right, but
the point of it is
that
He's making two important distinctions here about sin. They're kind of advanced distinctions
that again will play out in Christian and astaglit literature and other places.
One of course is between sins of thought and action.
Right.
Namely that you can sin in thought even if you don't do something.
Yeah, and this idea is of course one of Christ's major themes in the sermon on the Mount.
Right.
Yeah, you look at a woman lustfully you've already committed adultery in your heart
even if you haven't gone and taken any action, right?
If you hate your brother and your heart, you've already killed him, even if you've already
broken the commandment about murder, even if you don't go and actually harm him, right?
Yeah, so this is not something new in the gods.
Right.
And then, secondly, he says he's committed sins of ignorance, right?
And that's the distinction between sins of knowledge and sins of ignorance, right?
you don't have to sort of be consciously deciding
to do something bad in order to have sinned.
That you can sin unthinkingly.
That your intent is not the only thing that matters.
And the testament of Zebulin is arguing really
that not only are these things sinned,
Are there sins of thought?
and sins of ignorance that are truly sin. But it really wants to argue that they're just as bad.
Right. That even though he starts out by saying these are the only kinds of sins I've committed,
he's not saying that to say, therefore I'm better than most of you, he's saying that to say,
even though that's true, I'm still a sinner. Right. And again, as we've seen in a couple and we'll
We'll see in a couple more.
He goes back to...
the attempted murder of Joseph, his brother. And if you go read that story in Genesis,
Zebulin isn't mentioned in it, in the sense that like he didn't weigh in, he didn't
say anything on either side, he didn't say we should kill him, he didn't say no, we
shouldn't. He didn't say anything. And that's what the testament plays off of.
Yeah. So here's there's a kind of a sense of like you let it happen. And that means
you responsible as well.
Right.
That he was, he's an accomplice, right?
like he wasn't the one motivating it,
but he didn't do anything to stop it either.
Right? And so he participated in it just as much
as the brothers who were there and were talking
and were making the decisions,
because he was there and went along with it
and did nothing.
And so this is a very nuanced and developed
you'll see in it, participating in the sins of others.
and you can see how
Again, not only does a lot of monastic literature
and even examples in the New Testament
sort of grow out of these kind of ideas,
but you can see how further meditations on sin
and the understanding of sin and the fathers, right?
How this is sort of a link
between the Hebrew scriptures
and those kinds of understandings.
In terms of how Zebulin spent his life in a positive sense,
he's kind of paired off with Issaqar in a certain way
in that he-
presented as a fisherman. He actually claims to have invented the boat, the sail, and the rudder,
which is a little fishy part in the pun, given that Noah's Ark had already happened.
No sail and no rudder, but definitely a boat.
But this is not for the purposes of travel.
is a fishing. And so he's kind of presented parallel to Issacar like he's a farmer of the sea.
Instead of going to the ground and bringing food out of the ground, he's going and bringing food out
of the sea. And using the fish he catches to provide not only for himself and his family,
but it makes the point to also provide for the poor and those in need.
Yeah. So that's sort of an emphasis on, so again, right, if...
And that's parallel to the earlier part, right?
So if on the one hand, we want to make the point that these sort of sins of ignorance,
sins of thought, participating the sins of others is also serious sin, right?
Then the contrast to that, right?
The repentance of that is then that you not only provide for yourself and your family,
but you also then go and provide for others in a positive way, right?
you participate in doing.
good for others. And so we see sort of with Isaacard and Zabiel in a presentation of the
kind of life that should be pursued, not just the kinds of sins that should be avoided.
Yeah. All right. Well, we've done half the brothers. So we've got six more to go and we'll
handle those six when we get right back on this episode of Lord of Spirits. Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment.
to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
We venerate your immaculate icon, O Good Lord, and entreat you to forgive
our offenses, O Christ our God.
By your own choice, you were pleased to ascend the cross and the flesh to deliver us,
whom you created from our slavery to the foe.
Therefore we cry to you with gratitude.
You have filled all things with joy, O our Savior, by coming to save the world.
AthenaeUSA.com offers holy icons for those wishing to plant something spiritual in their souls.
Immaculate 22 karat gold leaf and applied on solid work.
Use the code Faith for free shipping.
Come and see it.
AtthamiteUSA.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back!
It's the third and probably final half of this episode of Lord of Spirits,
we're talking about the testaments of the 12 patriarchs and apocryphal text from
a century or two before Christ.
And before we move on with the final six of these testaments,
we're going to take a couple calls.
So we've got our old friend Samuel from Virginia who, I don't know,
I think Sammy, you might be the most frequent caller we've had.
What do you think?
Have you counted?
How many times have you been on the show?
A few.
A few. That seems about right.
It feels good to say that he truly is a number, a sufficient
a certain number.
So what is what is on your mind tonight, Sam?
You're from the Holy Land of Virginia.
I was wondering that it occurred to me last week, actually, that,
Well, in Jura.
was one of the things he's famous for is betray his brother. And in the New Testament,
there's someone with the same name who's also famous as a betrayer. How much did the early church
discuss that coincidence of names? I don't know, but I'll be fry hand it over to father. I will at
least say that there's another Judah, Judas in the 12, right, who didn't betray Christ, which is why
you know.
So it occasionally says Judas not a scary it said or Judas who would betray him said.
So I have to remember this is a really common name.
Is there any comparison made between the two father?
Yeah, not that I know of.
Not that I know of.
Like we think of Judas and we have this one idea about Judas, he's the betrayer but it's
Really common
name. Yeah. Oh yeah. No. No. I mean, it's just Judah. Yeah. So I mean, yeah. I mean,
one of the books of the New Testament is one of Bryce Brothers. Yes. Right. Do yeah.
I'm really trying to think if there's any. Yeah. I don't think there's definitely not
anything in the New Testament that goes in that. No. No, but you get, yeah. Most of what you get that's
It's focused on Judah the person is more about the Judah and Tamar episode.
Especially since Tamar shows up in Christ genealogy.
Yeah.
So you get more about that.
And that stuff is usually the typical...
Well, they talk about us for and why if you get the typical Gentile stuff.
And you know what I mean by that?
One of the go-tos of the Church Wathers in interpretation is, anytime somebody marries
a foreigner that's typological of Christ being the troving the Gentile Church to himself.
Yeah.
I'm going to have to say that.
I don't think there's really much for that dog, the hunt Samuel.
So yeah.
I'm even trying to think like in bridegroom mans where we talk about Joseph and
about. Joseph is portrayed as sort of like Christ, right? And yeah, it's a betrayal there. And I
don't I can't think of anything that draws that out that comparison. Yeah. Well, it was an idea.
So thanks, thanks for calling Samuel. Oh, he's good to speak with you. Okay. Oh, Tony,
I don't remember the proper response so well.
really he is, isn't? Alright, we're going to take another call. We have from the other
end of the country, Alexander from San Diego. So, Alexander, welcome to the Lord of Spirits
podcast. What is on your mind?
Three social SD.
Ali, athosan SD. So, my question being with Passover on my mind
after Popska here is what will Passover have in the worship cult of ancient Israel or
Thank you.
to the first, it said how it used to be that the elders would be sort of that take that
priestly role, but then that was taken away from them and given to the priest, but it seems
from Passover, my naive understanding is that it was performed by heads of families who
were practiced within families. So, is that kind of understood is still part of the worship cult?
I guess the Passover lamb considered part of sacrificial worship and what the understanding of that
and how that carries over.
Because obviously...
in the Christian context, it's our sort of the central
defining act of worship.
So to get answer that would be great.
Yeah, so Father, what's the liturgical shape of Passover?
How would you celebrate that prior to the coming of Christ?
Yeah, so that was done still by the head of the household.
And yeah, so there's a question
as to in what sense the Paschalam actually is a sacrifice.
In that, the family eats the whole thing.
Yeah, there's no part that's burnt up.
There's not a part that's actually offered to God.
And so it's a little bit of a different situation.
I think it is still sacrificial.
I think it is, I would say it is still sacrificial in the ritual sense.
Right, that the ritual surrounding it is a type of sacrificial ritual, even though there's
that big distinction there that separates it from like sin offerings, guilt offerings,
peace offerings.
And that of course is why they still do it right Jewish
Family still do it. Yeah, even though they don't have a temple anymore. Yeah
So there there are elements that and a certain type of thank offering that they will still do because those were not
Temple restricted
If somebody were to I don't know
So write a commentarian at St. John's Cost.
the whole thesis of which was dependent upon the idea that the high-pre-sacrifice
lambs that pass over, that would kind of all fall apart based on, you know, what's in the Torah.
With the listener understand, if you do.
But yeah, so it's a little bit different and that's why it is still a family and identity.
So it the Passover function.
very much in a way parallel to Passover itself, very much in a way similar to circumcision.
Right. Like circumcision wasn't done at the temple. Yeah. I mean, traditionally wasn't
it done by the father, but only later do you get the figure of the Moil? You get a
oil. Yeah, yeah. Who would be one of the elders of the community, right? Who just did it for everybody?
Right. So it was considered more, it was more at that, it remained at that level.
And, and was not really part of the temple cult. Now they did for practical reasons. So for
example, if you lived in Jerusalem or you were going to Jerusalem in the Passover,
they did physically kill a lot of lambs at the in the temple complex, right? But that was for
logistical and practical.
of having to draining blood and all those kind of things, right?
Like they were set up to slaughter animals there.
Whereas if you're living in a city on an average city block,
trying to slaughter a lamb and prepare it yourself there,
we kind of tough, right?
So for logistical reasons, but it's not like people who didn't go to Jerusalem
for the Passover didn't celebrate the Passover.
Right, and they didn't have priests functioning. Yeah
So yeah pass over is a little different and that's why
so
We've talked about this on the show before but what really generates the debate in Acts 15 what really generates the issue with
whether
non-Jewish Christians need to be circumcised.
was the continuity drawn between the Eucharist and the Passover.
So there's definitely continuity there. Right? There's continuity there because,
of course, Christ institutes the Eucharist at the Passover.
Right? Not at what comes to be called the Seder, but at a meal related to the Passover.
At the time of the Passover,
it's a participation of Christ, sacrifice, Christ sacrifices, self-offering takes place at the Passover.
at the Passover. They're always connections between the
in the Passover. While there were Jewish Christians who said, well, wait a minute, right?
Read the Torah. It's all fine for these Gentiles to come and live among us and worship our
God. Great. We're cool with that. But if they're going to eat the Passover, they're going
to receive the Eucharist. They need to be circumcised. That's what it says. Read the book,
right? The other side, right, Saint Paul's side, Saint Peter's side, beyond just what
they are with.
with the Holy Spirit and non-Jewish Christians was there are also discontinuities
between the Eucharist and the Passover. Like it's not once a year. Here what I say
Orthodox people, receiving the Eucharist is not once a year. Right, it started out
weekly and became daily.
So that's a discontinuity, right?
And it was for very early on called the Eucharist, which was connected to the thank offerings.
And the type of thank offering normally done at the beginning of the Sabbath was done
weekly, right?
That was one type of weekly thank offering.
So there's a continuity there that represents a discontinuity with the Passover.
And so...
That was involved in that argument too and the ultimate settlement was no the Eucharist is not eating the Eucharist is not
Directly comparable to eating the Passover
That it is it is a separate thing
So and a type of thank offering and a newly instituted sacrifice by Christ as his
Memorial so all that is to say
I
Hope that answered your question about the Passover
for what it's worth. Exodus 12, Exodus chapter 12, 27, both in the team James and Orthodox
study Bible will say like that you shall say, you know, this has not possible to sacrifice
it to Lord. So I mean, it seems like it is referred to as sacrifice. And maybe it's also connected.
I mean, where the first born were that weren't under the blood or sacrifice. I don't know.
So I don't know. It seems like there is a. Yeah. Well, there's the separate dedication to
the first board.
which involved a sacrifice also, right?
Where when you had a firstborn child or a firstborn animal you went and offered a sacrifice
to be at the temple. And that was very clearly a traditional sacrifice. You're taking it to the temple,
it's butchered, parts are offered to God, parts are eaten, right, etc.
Yeah, so the Passover is just sort of like I said, I believe it's a sacrifice, but it's
And it's different than it's distinguished from those others.
And that's why it never sort of gets becomes completely
part of the temple cult, right?
Using cult in the broad original sense,
not, you know, of the temple worship,
but remains sort of diffused and at the family and household
level.
All right, well Alexander thank you very much.
for calling. Yeah thank you. Christ and rhythm. He truly is risen. Okay we have six more brothers to
go and we're gonna start with. Yes we have bad rides for them. It's nice thank you very much for
that. Musical theater reference. I know the way to your heart. Yeah. Yeah okay so testament of Dan.
Yes, not short for Daniel either no
Dan. Yeah, the infamous Dan. Yeah, so as we've mentioned before, the scriptures have nothing
good to say about Dan or anyone descended from him, which is kind of sad, given, you know,
I mean, the actual person, the son of Jacob might have been fine, but, oh, well, but yeah,
is to say that it's all going south.
I said nothing good to say about anyone descended from him anyone from that
tribe there's there's a bunch of people right now like on social media going
crazy again like how dare you but yeah yeah
cry more I don't care stay mad the Dan is therefore rather appropriately
taking again to be an example of a passion.
And again, we go back to when Joseph is sold into slavery.
Dan, though, is clearly one of the ones who wants to murder him.
But in this case, rather than jealousy or that kind of thing,
it's sort of anger and wrath, sort of violent hatred.
He's just kind of a bestial dude.
and that caused him to want to kill Joseph, to sort of straight evil. And he gives this
interesting quote about why he didn't get to murder his brother. Right, right. Yeah, so he says,
but the God of my fathers did not suffer him to fall into my hands so that I should find him alone
and slay him. And cause he
second tribe to be destroyed in Israel. So second tribe, I mean, this is a reference to his
own tribe basically getting wiped out of Israel. Yeah, yeah, because of course Dan isn't there
in the book of Revelation. Right. He's the one who's not listed. So the second tribe in this case,
you know, under subjunctive sense, right, would be Joseph, you know. Yeah, would have been Joseph's,
would be if he had managed to get over.
of him. Right. I noticed that find him alone. Right. So Dan is saying he wanted to go full
cane, but like didn't manage to pull it off. Darn it. God didn't let him. Yeah. Didn't
even need like to make it a conspiracy with the other brothers. I was like, I'm just
going to take care of myself. Yeah. And you know, because the other brothers were around,
didn't get to kill him, right? Yeah. And this that talks about that
was sort of moved and motivated by the spirit of hatred and violence, which is here described
poetically the testament of Dan as the right hand of Satan.
He goes on to then quote the book of Enoch about his descendants in the tribe of Dan to
say that they're prints, right? They're prints of the sense that like
Michael was the Prince of Israel.
The Prince of the tribe of Dan would be Satan.
And they would be given to every kind of evil.
Yeah, no one has anything good to say about the tribe of Dan.
Yes, or anyone from it.
Yeah.
So, yes, so, uh, Testor of Dan,
it's right in with that with evil dew.
But notice here, right, remember, I know we had the break, we had a couple calls, but we're
coming off of Issaqar, Zebulin, right, the farmer and the fisherman, that kind of way
of life, right?
That quiet, peaceful life, working hard, right?
What's the exact opposite of that?
The spirit of hatred and violence and murder, right?
Debarring your brother.
Um
So, then after Dan, naphthaly, the testament of naphthaly, everyone's favorite brother,
all heard about him, thought so much about him.
It's not a name that gets used to often these days.
Yeah.
So this is another piece of the text, interestingly, that we know circulated independently.
Hmm, because we have a separate copy of just the testament of Nav.
from Kumron. Now, testament of Levi, you might have expected. Levi made your figure,
priestly figure, priesthood, lots of things to say about that. You could see why someone would
just write a testament of Levi, right? Apparently someone also just wrote a testament of
naphthaly. But naphthaly, there's like nothing about him in in Genesis. Right.
And not even very much about his descendants in the Torah and stuff.
And so this one goes in a real different direction.
This is another testament that involves apocalyptic,
an apocalyptic journey that actually Joseph is going to take,
not naftily himself, but Joseph.
even though Naphtali is in the text and narrating it to his sons.
And Nathalie is here taken to be sort of emblematic.
His tribe is one of the tribes that made up the Northern Kingdom of Israel.
Under Ephraim, the descendants of Joseph, right, where the kings came from.
It was part of that.
And so his tribe is here taken to sort of be a representative.
And this testament is used as a representative statement
to talk
about those ten northern tribes.
And they do try to incorporate the little tiny bit about
NAFTALE that is in the scriptures.
Specifically in the testament of Jacob in Genesis 49,
when he talks about NAFTALE, he compares him to a deer.
So there's like this sort of this deer motif.
stuff about deer running through the testament of naftily, but it's like
That's all they got right
We talked I know we talked about before I think it was back when we talked about Jewish astrology
That we talked about the fact that in the the testament of Jacob you see a lot of animals
Like the lion with Judah and the deer here and and
serpent with Benjamin.
There's these animal motifs that pop up.
And we talked about then that those were connected to 12 constellations,
which were connected to the 12 tribes.
And the symbols on the 12 stones for the 12 tribes that were on the E-FOOD
or the breastplate of the high priest had the constellations on them.
Right, that's...
That's what was engraved on them.
If that makes you super uncomfortable,
go back and listen to our Jewish astrology episode.
I'm not saying that'll make you more comfortable,
just you should go listen to it.
Yeah.
For more of this, discomfort.
So, there's again a quotation from the book of Enoch,
a quotation from the book of Enoch, the testament of naftily that's talking about
destruction of the northern kingdom of Israel because within the Hebrew
scriptures there is this tension because of course these tribes are gone but
within the prophetic tradition you read Ezekiel, you read Isaiah, you read
Chair.
Amaya, the promises about the new covenant and about the restoration of Israel are very
directly about the restoration of all 12 tribes.
It's about Judah and Ephraim being bound back together and being restored.
And Ephraim being the symbol of the 10 Northern tribes altogether.
And so we have to, a lot of second-templed Jewish literature is struggling with like, okay,
is.
What does that look like? How can that be? How would that work?
Right, how is that possible?
Right.
What do we do about that? And so the central part of the testament of naphtheli is really trying to
to envision that quite literally. So naphtheli has this vision
at the
Mount of Olives
Where are you?
standing with his brothers. And of course there's a little inaccuracy too that he's hanging out at the
Mount of Olives next to Jerusalem, which is a Jerusalem yet. It's this Jebyside city. But that's what happens.
So he has this vision at the Mount of Olives. And in it sort of he and his brothers are all
represented. Levi becomes the son.
Judah becomes the moon, right? You can see again this idea of the two
messiahs and of the
Levitical the priestly messiah being the greater one of the two and
Then the bowl of heaven appears
What? Yes a wild bowl of heaven appears. This is effective
Which is a giant bowl with wings
Right
And this scares all the brothers.
except for Joseph who jumps on it and rides it up into the heavens.
Okay, and so first of all, what?
But then after he has ascended into heaven on the back of the Bull of Heaven,
this giant scroll comes down and unrolls for NAFTALE to read.
And amongst other things, it says, and this is in test-serve of NAFTA-
5.8 that thus the Assyrians, the Meads, the Persians, the Ilamites, the Galachians, the Caldians,
and Syrians will gain a share in the 12 tribes of Israel through captivity. Literally says the 12
staves of Israel, but the word for staff and tribe is the same in Hebrew. So, no one knows who the
the glockians are. Yeah, you're looking for a
dissertation topic. Yeah, I mean, there you go. Who are the
go? If you search on that word, G-E-L-A-C-H-I-A-N-S, the only
references you will find to it is the test of an
epitome. Yeah, it is no other that we know of. Yeah. But
everyone else, who we do know of, the Assyrians, the
Meads, the Persians, the Elamites, the Caldians, the
serians these are all Mesopotamians right?
or people who ruled Mesopotamia at various points,
post exile.
So the Assyrians destroyed the Northern Kingdom.
Take all of the Israelites, relocate them.
They marry in over there.
And then the Caldience, the Meads, the Persians,
those Syrians.
That's where Israel is in exile.
And so, and that's why the bowl of heaven is used.
the bull of heaven is this symbol of Mesopotamia. So what's being shown in the
vision? What is the fate of Joseph representing here, the Ephraimites,
representing here the northern kingdom? They are not destroyed by the Caldians,
by the Mesopotamians. They are actually taken up into heaven by and with the
Caldience.
Right. And so what the text of the scroll then is making plain is that through them having
gone into captivity, right, what is actually going to happen is that those Gentile nations
are going to through them find salvation. Yeah, there's this integration through the
drives by becoming part of those tribes. Yeah. Yeah.
And this is this is playing off of in Genesis 48
but Joseph brings his two sons,
been asked an Ephraim to be blessed by Jacob.
Menastah is actually the older son,
but this is Genesis.
So Jacob crosses his hands,
it puts his right hand on Ephraim
and Joseph tries to correct him and he's like, no.
And Ephraim is told how great he's going to be
and how many descendents he's gonna have.
kings and all this. And then he says, and you will become the fullness of the Gentiles.
And there's only one other place in the Bible where that phrase occurs.
That's Romans 11,
where St. Paul says that once the fullness of the Gentiles has come in to be added to Judah,
then all of Israel will be saved.
So this is a current of thought that we see reflected here in the testament of naftily.
Right?
Where in the testament of naftily these Gentiles come into union with the head with Levi and Judah, with the Messiah,
It viscues the Messiah's but with the Messiah and through that become part of Israel and find salvation
Right, this is a way of thinking about this
Restoration that is exactly what St. Paul does.
Yeah.
In Romans and elsewhere.
Again, not making this up.
This is a current of thought, right?
This is pre-Christian, right?
But this is part of the tradition that St. Paul receives, right?
And that he keys in on in terms of the particular mission
that Christ sends him on to the nations.
and what it's gonna mean and how it's working that through the
Messiah the Gentiles are becoming part of Israel.
Right.
So that was all exciting.
Now the testament of GAD.
Good old GAD.
It can't all be hits guys.
Come on.
You got some deep album cuts to another name that doesn't get
used very often these days.
GAD.
Yeah, there's Josh GAD, but that's his last name.
Yeah. So, GAD, right? Another figure we don't have a lot of, right, in the Hebrew Bible,
or in Genesis or the Torah, or any place really. And so, again, we go to the attempt to kill Joseph.
But what's done here, and as I said, way back with the testament of Simeon, when I said
they were going to come back to this episode over and over again, they come at it from different
angles, right?
And so the particular angle here is wanting to make a contrast between hatred of your brother
and love for your brother.
And it wants to do that, not in order in this case to focus on the hatred or the attempted
murder but to focus on sort of defining the opposite.
Right. Meaning the opposite of not hating and wanting to murder your brother is not just
being meh toward your brother. Yeah, he's cool, whatever. Right. Like the opposite of
that is loving your brother. Yeah, actually giving yourself, you know, in self sacrifice
for another person came for someone else. And that as an actual concrete, definitely,
He said like a f-
or an emoteman, I love that guy.
I love you, man.
But it's actually doing things.
And in this case, right, it's particularly this contrast between, well, they wanted to murder Joseph.
What's the opposite of wanting to murder someone?
Wanting them to have a long and full and rich life.
Right. And again, it's not just the feeling of wanting that for them or wishing it to them.
but actually doing things for others
that help them have a more full, more rich,
longer, better life.
That's sort of the concrete nature of what love is.
And that sort of concrete love for your brother
right is taken to the extent even of,
well what do you do when that's not returned?
Right.
What do you do when you're doing all this for your brother and your brother hates you, right?
And is not being the same toward you, right?
Well, Joseph, again, Joseph's story is a good place to go with this, right?
And the testimony of God wants us to remember that vengeance belongs to the Lord.
Right. Where vengeance needs to be taken, where something is unjust and needs to be sorted out,
it out, God is going to sort that out.
Yeah, I mean, especially when it's about you, right?
You don't like take vengeance for yourself.
Now, if you can bring justice for someone else, if you can, in a good and righteous way,
right, that's cool, that's good.
Yeah.
That's part of showing love for them, right?
Exactly.
But yeah, you don't revenge for yourself.
Because number one, it belongs to God.
But number two, you don't even know everything that's gonna go
on. Like what if you know that person might repent at some point, right? You know there's
all kinds of possibilities. You just don't know enough to be competent to do that. Right.
Right. And so this idea of love for your neighbor, love being concrete, right? Loving even your
your enemies and those who treat you poorly, pre-Christian idea.
This is something that's already around for Christ then to refer to when he's preaching, right?
And teaching.
So then, number 10, the shortest one of them all, the testament of Asher.
Okay.
Again, not not someone we have a ton of material.
about probably why this is the shortest one.
The answer is actually a fairly common Jewish first name lately.
Yeah, especially the millennials.
I don't know why, but even Jewish communities apparently have these phases where people
get certain names.
The brothers of Joseph, the Bible, kind of like the dwarves in the Hobbit, right?
you got a list of names but there's not really a lot about most of them.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, the dwarves in Snow White, how much do we really know about most?
vague personality descriptions like bashful. Why is he so shy?
Come on.
Exactly. And Doc, what is up with that? Like, why is one called Doc?
Yeah.
Yeah, all the other ones are character traits.
What do they call a normal? He got the degree.
Can you have a normal name like Diffidence?
He must have been called something before he got the degree.
That's on.
Yeah, maybe he was on Wii before that.
I don't know.
What is his doctorate?
What is his doctorate even in?
Yeah, that's a good question too.
I would assume some kind of geology because they're minors.
Hmm.
Colorado School of Mines.
Yeah, I assume it was something applicable.
Yeah.
Could be a medical doctor.
Well, as we all know, medical doctors are real doctors.
You could be patching up patching up the others, right?
Unless they teach yeah
Okay, test would have Asher. Yeah, it's sleepy. Just needed some some caffeine man. Yeah, anyway
So yeah, test would have Asher shortest one and
Also kind of the most general because of that
It's really picking up.
on what is commonplace in Jewish wisdom literature. This idea that there are two ways or two roads, two paths
that you could follow. You could follow one that leads to good, one that leads to evil,
one that leads to good is hard, one that leads to evil's. Easy, right? But you find this
in proverbs, you find this in other Jewish wisdom literature. You find this in early Christian
literature like the D.D.K.
It's all over the place.
The sort of angle of the testament of Asher that's a little bit interesting is that it kind of addresses
Thursemiques from Plato's Republic in that it talks about how
faced with those two ways of living their life. What most people actually want to do and tend to do?
is they want to pursue evil, but they want to look good.
They want to look like they're a good person,
while they're pursuing evil, have their cake and eat it too.
Yeah, hypocrisy.
Yeah. Of course, big problem with that,
as Testament of Ashrepoids out, is that you can trick people with that,
you can't trick God with that,
because God knows what's in your heart,
and so that duplicity
isn't going to work.
And he also talks a little bit about how goodness always has to be, or is always open
in genuine in the sense that
Someone can lie and hide. Some people will try to lie and hide evil. Right. Right.
So they'll do evil and pretend to be good. Right. But you don't see anyone doing good and
pretending to be evil. Right. And so
You shouldn't be looking for, there's nowhere down the evil path where you will find anything
good or true.
You may try to walk the good path and up falling into error, falling into sin, because of
your struggles in following that path, right?
But the opposite isn't true.
Therefore, there's no reason to ever go down that road.
He's advising his sons and his descendants.
Right?
It's not like going down the path of evil and sin
is a mixed bag.
You could maybe find something interesting over there.
Right.
So yeah, so that's the short little testament of Asher.
And then you come to the testament of Joseph.
All right.
Now again, something really good.
And Joseph is of course interested figure.
We've already alluded to this because of course,
a third of the book of Genesis is the story of Joseph.
Yeah, it's probably one of the longest,
it's not the longest biographies we get in the scripture, I think.
Yeah.
Maybe David, but.
Bye.
Yeah, so Joseph, right, massive, a third of the book of Genesis, right?
And if you're starting at the beginning of the Bible,
or even just the beginning of the Torah and reading through it, you would assume
coming off the last page of Genesis that because you kind of have the person
you're following is like the line of the promise, right?
You go from Abraham to Isaac to Jacob, right?
And there you come.
I go to Joseph for a third of the book of Genesis.
But then as you go forward to the Hebrew, the rest of the Torah,
that the Hebrew Bible, right?
Like Ephraim, Manasseh, not a lot good going on there,
and then like they just disappear to the ascetics.
Joseph doesn't end up being, he's not a...
The ancestor of the Messiah.
Right.
Judah, Levi, right, these week of the important trip.
But Judah and Levi, the people, are not the focus of a third of the book of Genesis.
Right?
Yeah.
This, to me, is one of the best arguments.
And I have heard no good counter-argument for the antiquity of the book of Genesis, at least, within the Torah.
Yeah, because if you're a later writer trying to establish the glory of your line
And you don't spend a third of your primary book focusing on a guy that you're not even
descended from.
Right.
And conversely, and conversely, if Ephraim was essentially already gone, right?
Why would you have and be preserving and presenting as so important these Joseph traditions?
Yeah.
Right.
Yeah, right.
But to me, that's kind of a good strong argument that I've never heard a good counter
argument to, that genesis has to be older than the divided kingdom.
It's in something like its current form, which may not sound like a big deal, but trust
me, well, it has to with studies.
That's a wild claim.
But again, give me a good counter argument to that.
But so Joseph obviously very important in the Torah, the Torah very important to the author of the
Testament of the 12 page arcs, but the same time he's writing at the beginning of the second century BC
where Ephraim is long gone. Right? And we've seen in the Testament of Naftali, which may not be written
by the same person who wrote the Testament of Joseph. They very well not be. He does have it, but
But the t-
as a whole has a destiny in mind for the Ephraimites and the rest of the Northern Kingdom.
It's still Joseph is not the the lead figure in that, right? Even within that vision in the
testament of Naphtali, it's Levi and Judah who are the heads, right? Who Joseph and the rest of
the Northern Kingdom. Their Gentile.
quote unquote descendants come into fellowship with that brings about their
salvation, not Joseph himself. Joseph isn't the key figure.
So Joseph here in the Testament is primarily, well first of all there's two pieces to
it. The first piece is Joseph is used to represent the virtue of
Right, not just chastity.
within marriage, but Chastity in the broader sense. And that's by focusing on the episode
between him and Potiphar's wife, who attempted to seduce him in the book of Genesis,
and he resisted and ended up thrown in prison because of it after she claimed he raped her.
Yeah, and I didn't put it in the notes, but it actually gives a name for her in this text,
which of course in Genesis, she's not named. She's just called Potiphar's wife.
Yeah, I guess and or something like that.
It's
also dramatized here the testament of Joseph where she's doing all this
stuff threatening to kill herself and doing all this stuff to try to get him to
sleep with her but won't do it. So there's that element of chastity, preserving
chastity, and you know father Andrew referenced the great canon of St. Andrew
earlier. You can see this emphasis on the episode with Joseph and Potiphar's
That's why I've-
there, you can see it in some of the hymns about Joseph and Brian Grumatins in Holy Week,
still fresh in my brain because we did it so recently. This whole idea of Joseph as this
representative of Chastity in that case. There's also another reminder about seeking revenge,
which Joseph of course famously did not do.
But the probably
the other and more major, more interesting to a lot of people, part of the
testament of Joseph is there's another apocalyptic section. Instead of a vision
with him, it's a dream that he has, which is kind of appropriate because
remember Joseph is all about interpreting dreams. Right. He's the big dreamer.
In Genesis. So he has this dream and this is this is a dream about the Messiah.
Right, who is going to come?
Now this
This is one of those interesting textual places, because there's an aromatic version and
there's a Greek version that we have.
We have both the whole text for the testament of Joseph.
And the dream in particular, so this dream we're going to see, there's a bunch more on the
nose sounding kind of things about the Messiah.
that scholars are gonna wanna say are...
Christian interpolations, right?
But here's the problem.
The aero-mayek version, in particular of the dream,
is longer than the Greek version.
Hm.
The Greek version is shorter.
So when the Greek version is shorter,
and they're arguing that the Greek version is the Christian
version where they added things, your antennae should go up.
Right?
Wait a second.
things, it's shorter, right? And so you might ask then, okay, so if your hypothesis is the Greek
version is the Christian version and it's way shorter, then let's look at the stuff that gets left
out. Is there a reason why Christians would have left out that stuff that gets left out?
I'm out.
I can surf.
certainly. If the stuff that got left out was stuff that didn't match up with Christianity.
Right. And then the Greek version just kept the stuff that did match up with Christianity.
You might have a case. But guess what? It done. Right. So it's not an easy just doesn't
work out. Yes. The stuff in the air make version that gets left out of the Greek version
Not only doesn't have any related...
the relationship to Christianity, detectable whatsoever, but it's also stuff that's found in the other testaments.
In the Greek versions, it's the same kind of material.
So if you're going to say the Greek version is the Christian version, why would they cut it out here and not cut it out in those other places?
Right so it's very clear that the Greek version is not the is not a Christian version per se it's just a Greek translate
right? It's just a Greek version. So that already is a strike against a shorter Greek version,
which is a strike against the idea that Christians added things. That's not a particularly Christian
version, but we'll get to the particulars here in a minute. Most of the dream is similar to something in
the book of Enic that we'll talk about at some future point in more detail, but there's a section of
of the Book of Enic, a first enic that has a-
called the Animal Apocalypse, which is not what used to happen when I would go to the
Pope Isbefe here in Lafayette, Louisiana.
I think it would make a great title for a limited run comic book series.
Oh, I was thinking just of a fai.
The Animal Apocalypse.
Some kind of carnivore diet buffet.
uh... the animal apocalypse
again this is a apocalypse in the sense of revelation it's called the animal
apocalypse because in the book of Ianic it sort of retells the history of
Israel but with all of the biblical characters portrayed as different
animals right so CS Lewis not an original idea in his life but anyway I mean so
That's the writers thing.
That's just like your opinion man.
Yeah, right.
Oh, I agree.
It's just like a laguman on men.
So, so you have something like that.
It is this green that Joseph has.
Where he gives sort of a brief history with people presented
as animals.
But this one just runs from the exile to the Hasmonians,
meaning the king's post-mack-a-be-
in revolt to his day. So just covering a couple hundred years there, which is one of the
ways we peg down when it was written, because it kind of goes up to the then current day.
the more interesting parts that are included here, which again are thought to be...
The first one is, of course, it says that the Messiah is going to be born of a virgin from the tribe of Judah.
What?
Immediately people say, oh, Christians added that.
Christians added that. That could be a pre-Christian text.
I be a virgin birth. It's not like that exact same word was used in Isaiah 7.
Oh, wait it was right there was
Never mind. Never mind. Right? So, yeah, but this this is what we're dealing with your people.
This is what we're dealing with your people. This is why when people come out and say,
well, Father Jesus says this, but Old Testament scholarship says, X, Y, Z, as if they can speak
for Old Testament scholarship. But anyway, you know, like, I laugh them to score. Right? Because
This is this is
level of thing we're dealing with. This says that the Messiah is going to be born of a virgin.
That's a Christian idea. That must have been added, even though it's just using the exact same
Greek as Isaiah 7. Which they would agree is pre-Christian. Okay. This is why in order to get a Ph.D.
In this country or any other, you should have to take a logic course.
just one. One like it would be an undergrad level logic course. I don't care. You need to take one.
In sort of the drama, right, of the Messiah coming, right? So it goes up to the then present day
and then talks about the Messiah coming. Messiah is presented as a lamb
and who does...
battle with and defeats a bunch of reptiles and creeping things.
And it's important that he doesn't do battle with.
He doesn't do battle with the animals that represent the other nations.
It's not the Messiah versus the Gentiles.
It's the Messiah versus the reptiles and creeping things that represent the evil spirits,
Right. Who are motivating and...
and provoking the nations.
And then ultimately those nations again,
once again, in keeping with what we've already seen,
find salvation through Levi and Judah.
But now are you ready for the most on the nose piece?
I'm ready.
The Greek of Testament of Joseph 1911
Says, refers to the Messiah as
the Lamb of God who will take away the sins of the world.
What?
That's gotta be an interpolation.
That's gotta be.
When that's straight out of...
St. John's Gospel.
Gospel of John.
Yes.
Or is it?
That's gotta be.
Right, right.
Unless we think about this for a second,
because we had a logic class once in our life, okay?
When St. John the Baptist says that in St. John's Gospel,
in the hospital.
He says, behold the Lamb of God who takes away the sins of the world.
What is he doing?
He's identifying Jesus as the Messiah.
He points at Jesus.
He says that.
Right.
Everyone understands.
Everyone who hears that understands that he's identifying Jesus as the Messiah.
Yeah.
And in that line, right, the Lamb of God, okay, that's Passover stuff.
takes away the sum of the world, that's do you have a tonement stuff?
Right, swish together. Yeah. I mean, he's just, he's just using stuff from the old test of it.
Right. Right. But so he says that they all understand that means he's the Messiah.
Yeah. Would they have all understood that if he just made it up on the spot?
Right. Yeah, he's making reference. Right. Would they?
especially since he's Mishvashik, Passover and damn...
a Tobit stuff? Yeah. These are prepoints at this person. Says, behold the Lamb of God who takes away
the sins of the world. And they don't all stand there and go, wait, what? Right. He's the Lamb of God
and what sense? What does that mean? So they'll go out Passover. He's going to take away the sins of
the world. How? What does that mean? Why do they all immediately know that means the Messiah?
Could be.
Let me just throw this out here, Occup's razor.
That was symbolism that had already been applied to the Jewish Messiah in different places.
One of them being here, right?
In the testament of Joseph.
And if there were already texts like this, that were doing things with animal symbolism
that kind of thing. Right? Let's suppose that this was originally there in the pre-Christian document,
the testament of the 12 Patriots. Right? So this was symbolism that people used. This was a way that
people had talked about the Messiah before that as soon as Saint John did that, what? Everyone would
go, oh, he's saying that person is the Messiah. Yeah, it wouldn't be effective, effective rhetoric,
if no one knew what he meant.
Yeah.
And Lord behold what we would expect if this was original and pre-Christian is exactly
what happens in St. John's Gospel.
Yeah.
So again, right, why would you want to argue that this is pre-Christian?
Right? It's just proceeding from a presupposition.
It's proceeding from this presupposition that Christianity is this whole new set of ideas
that came from nowhere, fell out of the sky, yet still isn't true, in the first century
with no connection to any preexisting religion.
Which makes no sense.
And if you wanted to argue it literally fell out of the sky in the first century and had
no precedence in human religion.
And you believed it was true and came directly from...
God, that would at least make sense.
Right? But it both evolved and didn't evolve for preexisting religious traditions.
Right? And it's both not supernatural at all but also completely disconnected.
And right? And you find yourself in this bizarre position. You don't have to be.
Even if you're an atheist, you don't have to do that much work, man.
Just say like yeah, that was
Jewish way of talking about the Messiah. Yeah, it shows up with the New Testament. And you know,
maybe you don't believe it's true. Is that so hard? Is that really so rough? Do we have to
contort history? Do we have to do all this ledger domain about tax and dividing them up and which
line is from when? No, you don't. You can see, you know, just say you don't believe it.
And of that ran.
Okay.
Last but not least, the testament of Benjamin.
All right.
Number 12.
The Kaboos.
And so one thing that's unique about the testament of Benjamin is that as we've seen,
right, most of these are sort of directly connecting the person, the son of Jacob and
their descendants in various ways.
Yeah.
Right.
Dance Assendants are all
rotten, so Danis presented is rotten, right?
The test of revengement on the other hand actually wants to disambiguate between the person Benjamin the son of Jacob and his descendants
and
That's because there's a certain ambivalence about his descendants
Yeah, I mean one of them being saw right yeah, so there's an ambivalent
about his descendants. So it's not as clear cut as his descendants are all bad, right? And so he's
going to be presented as having a bunch of bad descendants, but also some other descendants who
are good descendants and those good descendants are going to be seen to be the ones who actually
take after Benjamin their father. Right. So you see this ambivalence in the way Benjamin
the person is treated in Genesis, right? Where he's sort of this good kid who everybody loves,
right? Yeah. Especially his father, maybe a little too much at the expense of his brothers, but
right? He is this good kid, but then in Genesis 49 in the testament of Jacob, you know, he's like
this ravting wolf, right? You're like, oh, time out, right? Like, this is weird, right? And that's
describing the Benjamites are going to cause a civil war in Israel and the book of judges.
Saul is going to be from the tribe of Benjamin, right, and it's going to be Judah that ends up with the kingship, right?
So you've got this problematic element of the Benjamites, plus they're all left-handed, which is sinister.
Then on the other hand, Benjamin as a tribe stays with Judah when the other tribes break away.
It sort of remains faithful and survives.
Goes into exile with Judah, comes back with Judah, right?
So there's this ambivalence.
And there's within the text of the testament of Benjamin,
there's sort of this analogy made between Benjamin's relationship
relationship with Joseph.
brothers of the same mother, right? Their relationship and the kingdom being taken from Israel, right?
Because it's sort of what Joseph is separated from Benjamin. He goes off and becomes a king.
And in the same way, at the time of the exile, the kingdom was taken away from Judah.
Right, but with the hope then that just like Benjamin
in Joseph or reunited that there is this restoration and reunion coming.
And like the last couple of testaments we talked about then at the end of the Testimative
Benjamin, there's this sort of final prophecy element.
This one interestingly, the Greek is longer and the Aramaic is shorter.
So it's the opposite of the Testimative Joseph.
Yeah.
So this goes back to what I was saying at the beginning.
There's not a clear rhyme or reason to the like
languages. Right. If the Aramaic was all across the board shorter, everybody would say,
oh, well, it came first and then the Greek, right? Or vice versa, but it's not. It's
It's a bit more weirder than that.
It's more complicated than that.
But in this prophecy,
here we go again.
It talks about the Messiah who's referred to as Spock.
about him being seized by lawless men, about him dying for impious men, right? Even crazier, right?
In the Greek version, they use the phrase Lamb of God in Savior of the world.
Yeah, which just as a point, Savior of the world is not... I mean, it gets used, of course, in the Gospels,
but Caesar Augustus uses a tree for himself.
Yeah
This is not some uniquely Christian or even uniquely biblical title.
Yes, yes.
And of course, we talked about Lamb of God just now already.
Yeah.
And it talks about how the blood of the new covenant is going to save Israel and the nations
by purifying them of the works of Balaal.
We've talked about Balaal before the Yoke was the one, the Law was the one, right, the devil.
The blood is going to purify, purge away the works of the devil.
Set the...
a lot of the new covenant, right? So again, clearly, all this is stuff that Christians added
in the Greek. And look, the Greeks longer this time, right? Okay. Right. So we've already
had the previous testament. The Messiah depicted as a Passover lamb, right? Yeah. What was one
of the qualities that the lamb had to have.
to be the Passover Lamb. It had to be spotless. So referring to the Messiah's spotless, just
a continuation of that symbolism. Right? Seize by Lawless Medi for Ipius Men. This whole
testament has been a meditation on the relationship between Benjamin and Joseph. What happened to Joseph?
Lawless Men seized him, tried to kill him, sold him a slavery. Yeah. Okay. So this is just
taking part
the story of Joseph and applying it to the Messiah. Okay, again, nothing weird or
particularly Christian about that, right? The blood of the new covenant. There's
blood of the old covenant, right? Why wouldn't there be blood of the new
covenant? Why is that only a Christian idea? Right? And the idea of blood
purifying things again, day of atonement.
Right, Torah idea, not a purely Christian idea per se, and the idea of the purified for the works of Bala'il,
got bad news for you, that's all over the book of Enic.
Ed's second Enic, and the apocalypse of Abraham, and about five other second-devil Jewish texts.
Right, you're not going to be able to argue that all of those are
Christian interpolations because we have copies of those texts from
Kumaran and stuff that never touched Christian hands.
So no none of this stuff is Christian interpolations.
And for all the reasons I said in the previous rant it's ridiculous to try and
argue so. Just say yes. Christians made use of pre-existing Jewish ideas that
they applied them to Jesus of Nazareth who they believed to be the Messiah
because they believe in eros
the dead, right? You don't believe that. So you disagree. Fine, whatever, right? Move on with your life.
Yeah. So yeah, the ultimate kind of message that of the test生 of Benjamin is,
and this kind of sets it up as the antipode to the testament of Simeon, remember who was Envious of all
all these things about Joseph. Right, and that led to hatred,
where's Ben?
like loves everything about his brother Joseph and so is arguing rather than
hating so for those you should seek to emulate those qualities, right, to be
more like Joseph. And this is an important example of holding up a saint and
their life as something for emulation and devotion, which of course is going to
become a commonplace of Christian literature.
Indeed.
Well, we made it through all 12.
Good job.
So some of my takeaways from this little walk through
the testaments of the 12 patriarics.
Obviously, there's a lot more that could be said.
There's a lot of other details that are in those texts.
It's worth reading them.
None of them are really long.
I mean, we mentioned somewhere longer,
somewhere shorter, but none of them are really long.
Like you could read the whole thing within.
I don't know, maybe an hour, probably, I think. If you read all of it.
But the details that you picked, Father, I think serve a really important purpose, which is that they show this continuity between the religion of ancient Israel and the religion of the followers of Jesus Christ.
Jesus Christ.
And that really they are not two separate religions even.
So maybe continuity isn't even really the right word.
Like it's just simply the same religion.
It's simply the same one thing.
And but that certain events happen,
namely that the Messiah comes,
he dies and rises from the dead.
And so then what was always believed about the Messianic age
now has been inaugurated, right?
So it's not some other religion with some other
theology and whatever, it's simply that, oh, this has happened now. So, okay, now is what we do.
Right? And I think that this is important for a bunch of reasons. One of the reasons is that
the only way to really understand the New Testament correctly and Christian theology correctly
is within the context of everything that has come before it. Right? And we have this idea sometimes
that there is all that Old Testament saw.
And now Jesus came and he liberated it for us from all of that right? I've had people literally say that to me
Especially when we talk about the Old Testament at all people like but didn't Christ come to save us from that like wait a minute hold on a second
He's the logger
He's the one who gave the Torah why would he?
Set that whole thing up and then say ha ha
Psych you know like some new religion now that's not at all
what he came to do. And of course, we talked about that in some detail, we talked about this question of
fulfilling the law rather than abolishing it a few episodes ago.
So there's that. A correct understanding of Christianity requires a full understanding of the
the Torah and of all the Old Testament, but also on a very practical level.
Not that I don't think anything I just said was not practical, but to bring it down to
even an even finer level, right, is that I think that the way that we think about the
new testament and its relationship to the old testament, and often the way that we disconnect
them, right?
And maybe you don't believe you should do that, but, but, at least English speaking culture
is saturated with that idea.
the right like out with the old in with the new. This creates a habit of thought and
a habit of speech of discussion in which we look at things in isolation from their pretty
obvious context, right? And I mean, and you know, we've mentioned that a bunch of times
in terms of scholarly mistakes in this episode, right?
Like, oh, saying the Messiah would be born of a virgin, like that's crazy.
It must be some kind of Christian interpolation.
But it's right there in Isaiah.
It's right there.
Right?
Like the Bible, have you read it?
You know, the problem there is to look at stuff in isolation.
And then with a whole bunch of assumptions, like these are Christian things to say,
the Eards are Jewish things to say, and never the tween shall meet.
I'm sorry, that's not how this thing works.
even a-
from the question of, from explicitly theological issues like this, right?
This habit of mind that we have of de-contextualizing everything, right?
There are certain cases in which that is, that can be useful to isolate a thing
and to focus only on that one thing.
Fine. But for most things in life, it's not.
It's not.
And I don't mean it just
in terms of our theological understanding, but I also mean it in terms of practical
day to day living.
I'll give you a great example.
We just went through Lent and Holy Week and so forth.
And there are people that will take on, say, fasting, for instance, in some way, but then
don't also increase or alter their private prayer and then their corporate prayer together
with the church.
Right, so they do this one thing.
and fasting and say, I'm doing, I'm doing lent.
Well, if you can't, you know,
if you don't have the ability to increase your prayer
for some reason, especially corporate prayer,
maybe your prayers doesn't have those services
or you live a long ways away, whatever, fine.
But there are people who do it in a kind of illegalistic way
like I'm doing it and this is correct.
And but they're doing it in isolation
from the whole context of what it means to be Christian.
Right? Or let's say they're,
working on various ministries of taking care of things in the church, but they're not engaging in any kind of kind of almsgiving. They're not being charitable.
These things go together.
They form part of a seamless garment, right?
But also even just like interpersonal relationships.
Think about how many times when you have an argument with someone that you love, I hope.
You have an argument where you fixate on what that person said or what you didn't say.
I read recently if you if you really want to have a three or four hour argument in which nothing good is accomplished and everybody goes to bed really angry with each other just say these magic words. That's not what I said.
And you're sure to get there, you know, take it right there.
But what is that habit of thought all about it's all about isolating what you said or what the other person said and trying to render judgment on its correctness or
or you know, fuck.
or whatever and missing the point of the whole thing, which is that other person, and the
love that you supposedly have for them, right? When you seek to justify yourself in isolation
from trying to have a justified situation, a justified relationship, then you just destroy
it, right? Just as you look at different parts of Scripture and isolation or elements of Orthodox
tradition and isolation, you destroy it.
You rip apart the seamless garment
It's got to all go together
Right even you know humans are whole persons. You can't just fixate on
This one thing or this one other thing or like you don't love me if you do x1z
Meanwhile the person is slaving and self-sacrificing in so many other ways
But you don't do x1z therefore you don't love me like well hello. You're the ones supposed to be loving
Let God
Take care of that other person.
and what they're supposed to be doing,
you do what you're supposed to be doing, right?
And so when these things are brought together
and they're no longer handled in isolation,
then there's not just the whole picture
that emerges so you can see clearly, but definitely that.
But also there is a wholeness of life,
and there is the ability to give each other slack,
and there is wisdom that we have.
Like the wisdom that
comes from arms giving helps us to correctly administer the property of our homes and of our churches.
If you're not engaged in arms giving, you're not going to have the wisdom to do that stuff well.
Right? A good example is there are parish councils that basically function like building maintenance
societies, and they're not engaged in ministry that just take care of a building. I mean, it's important
to take care of the building. But if there's not this homesgiving wisdom that comes that is
required, then it's not going to work well, right? Or let's say the people taking care of
the building are not really engaged in worship. They're taking care of a building that they themselves
don't even use for its purpose. Right? So, I mean, you can imagine a hundred different ways that
this gets applied. And I think I'm not going to say that this sort of solar scriptura mentality,
and even this kind of law versus gospel mentality, you know, how...
are we going to split it apart people?
That's the origin of all those habits of thought,
but they sure do go together.
And so I think that one of the things
that sets of texts like the Testaments of the 12 Patriarchs
does for us is it makes us set aside
a lot of our assumptions and categories
that are not really applicable and see, like,
wait a minute, wait a minute, this all connects.
It's really one thing.
that even though
Text like this, we don't treat it as scripture, we don't regard it as being
Inspired in the same way that
You know that the Torah and the prophets and the apostles and so on and so forth are
Nonetheless, it shows like this is what the people of this time in place believed and wow it connects in both directions
That's my biggest takeaway from all of that and not just to learn this thing
right and to be amazed at how amazing it is.
is that it all sticks together.
Although that's cool, I mean, that's great.
That's, you know, beginning with that sense of wonders
of great place to start,
but to apply it within our own lives
and not to treat things in isolation,
to realize that they're all related.
I'm related to my family, to my friends, to my community.
I'm related to all of them,
and they together, the relationship that we have
with each other is what is who we are.
Right, and that we can't we can't dissect because when you dissect then you kill.
So that's that's what I have to say about all that.
So Christianity is a religion not a relationship.
It is true that the Church is the
the bride of Christ. It is true that often the life of the world to come is portrayed in
Scripture as the wedding supper of the Lamb. That does not mean that our Lord and God
and Savior Jesus Christ is your boyfriend.
Yeah.
Well, that concretely means is that...
Christianity as a religion has a history, it constitutes a tradition. There's a way of living
contained within it. There is a way of being in the world contained within it. There are
teachings that are contained within it. There are traditions and ways of doing things that are
contained within it. And these are not sort of individually up for grabs.
And I know we have a lot of listeners who at various points in their life were taught.
Maybe even taught that it was mandatory that they build their own Christianity.
That what was really important was their relationship, was that they loved Jesus.
And it's good.
I want everyone to love Jesus.
It's good to love Jesus.
that's what's really important and then every
Anything else, it is your duty to sort of figure out yourself.
So you look at all these individual issues, what isn't as an ascent.
This are that theological point.
This are that practice.
You read some Bible verses, you listen to some people speaking, you read some books maybe.
And you make your decision.
Here's where I stand on this.
is what I'm going to do.
And so you sort of shape your own way of life with some input from some Christian people
and some Christian texts and some input from the scriptures.
You choose all these things.
You try to keep out of your head the fact that the stakes are kind of high.
And if you don't do this right, you can end up going to hell or something.
depending on where you come down on the existence of L.
Then you form this thing, you just assert as Christianity, but here's the thing that
thing you made can't do what Christianity does.
Because what Christianity does by existing in this full orbed way is a full tradition.
There's a way of life and a way of being and a way of seeing things.
What it does is it changes and transforms people.
people. And if I mold Christianity around myself, around my own thoughts and feelings and
ideas and what I accept and what I'm persuaded by, if I mold it around me, then it can't mold
me in return. And it is ideally suited to me remaining the same. That's not self
in salvation, remaining the same.
In order to be molded and shaped,
we need to be scraped at, bent,
even maybe broken, and put back together.
That's how you get changed and transformed.
The most important parts of the Christian tradition,
the most important parts of Christianity.
are the ones that seem the most wrong to you.
The most important scriptures for you to read and meditate upon are the ones you don't like.
Are the ones that you find confusing and upsetting?
Are the ones that tell you that something you don't want to think is as in as a sin?
Are the ones that tell you that you need to do something that you don't want to do?
Those are the most important.
and those are the first ones out the door. If we don't accept the Christian
tradition as it has historically existed, as it has come down to us. The whole
body, all the writings, not just the scriptures, not just the things we want to
decide our scriptures. All of the teachings, all of the ideas, all of the thoughts,
the whole tradition.
And that is expressed, again, not just in this intellectual sense, either.
This is an actual living thing of actually living your life and actually living your life
publicly and in a community somewhere.
Because a community, an actual community, an actual parish, an actual church has a very
important role in this. And you being shaped and you being changed.
and you being transformed.
And the most important people to that, again,
are the people in that parish who you like the least,
who you get along with the worst,
who you most don't want to spend time with.
Because they're the ones who are going to scrape at you.
They're the ones who are going to make you bend.
They're the ones who may break you at a certain point.
And you have to be put back together.
They're the ones that are hardest to love,
so they'll teach you what love is.
They're the ones who are hardest to be joyful
around so they'll teach.
what joy is. They're the ones who it's hardest to have peace around so they'll
teach you what peace is.
That means that means not only do you don't get to pick your Christianity, you
really shouldn't even try to pick your parish.
You should go to the closest one, even if they do everything in a foreign language.
Even if the people there are welcoming and don't roll out a red carpet for you.
Right?
I don't see anywhere in the Scriptures or anywhere in our tradition.
That says that a Christian is entitled to have everyone in their parish be nice to them.
Or like them at all.
That's certainly not Saint Paul's experience when he traveled around going to different Christian communities.
They really just rolled out their ed carpet.
Loved him and thought he was the best.
Right? He didn't say, well, you guys are lousy Christians. I'm going to go someplace where I'm welcome and where they like me.
Saint Paul understood that he needed to be transformed and he understood that all the hardships he went through helped do that.
So all this is to say, when we're talking about texts like this, texts that are part of the Christian tradition,
important parts in the case of the text we talked about tonight, very important parts of the Christian tradition.
The fact that not so much the fact that people don't know about them, but that there's so many people out there who don't care about them,
Who would want to argue that they're irrelevant?
Who want to argue that they're not important?
Because they're...
form for themselves a Christianity in which that's true.
It shows the danger, the danger that we're in, of a world where you can completely divorce
yourself from the Christian tradition and think and claim and incest that you're a Christian
nonetheless.
How dangerous that is for people.
How easily that can lead you down the road you don't want to go down.
the road that leads.
to Christ. So I want to encourage everyone listening, as we approach Christianity, the Christian
religion, which is the way in which we approach Christ himself, the Jesus who we love.
It's not a question of what we can or want to or feel like we can, or won't accept about
the Christian tradition. It's a question of how...
How do I locate myself within it?
How do I interface with it?
Where do I find it?
Where do I plug into it?
So that I can be changed in such a way that maybe even some of those parts that I didn't
like or hated before I now love.
Because I have a better understanding of who Christ is.
and that allows me to love Jesus even more.
Amen.
Well, that's our show for tonight.
Thank you very much, everyone, for listening.
If you didn't happen to call us and call into us live,
we'd select to hear from you.
You can email us, LordofSpiritsDantianFate.com.
You can send us a message at our Facebook page.
You can leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash LordofSpirits.
And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity
Christianity or you need...
help to find a parish, head over to orthodoxintro.org.
And join us for our live broadcast of the second and fourth
Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern, 4 p.m. Pacific.
Except this month, when it'll be the fifth Thursday
instead of the fourth, but there's something coming on
the fourth, too.
It'll be interesting.
And you know, life was looking up for me when I left home.
It seems like yesterday.
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page to enter
discussion group, leave reviews and ratings
in all the appropriate places, and share the show
with your friends who are going to benefit from it.
Follow me, search.
to go to AncientPafeth.com, Stoke Support, and I'll make sure we, and lots of other AFR
podcasters, stay on the air. Now I'll never go back there again. Here is where I'll stay.
Thank you. Good night. Christ has risen. God bless you all.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener supported presentation of
ancient faith radio. And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne
and the beasts and the elders and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of
thousands, saying with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.
In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.
He was in the beginning with God.
All things were made through Him, and without Him nothing was made that was made.
In Him was life, and the life was the light of men, and the light shined in the darkness,
and the darkness did not comprehend it.
There was a man sent from God whose name was John.
This man came for a witness to bear witness of...
the light that all through him might believe. He was not that light, but was sent to bear
witness of that light. That was the true light which gives light to every man coming into
the world. He was in the world and the world was made through him, and the world did not
know him. He came to his own, and his own did not receive him. But as many as received
him. To them he gave the right to become children of God, to those who believe in his name.
who were born, not of blood, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of man, but of God.
And the word became flesh and dwelt among us, and we beheld His glory. The glory is of the
only begotten of the Father, full of grace and truth. John bore witness of Him and cried out,
saying, this was He of whom I said, He who comes after me is preferred before me, for He was before
me and of his fullness we
have all received and grace for grace. For the law was given through Moses, but grace
and truth came through Jesus Christ. A reading from the Holy Gospel according to St. John,
on great and holy Paska. It is the day of resurrection. O people, let us glory in splendor. Paska,
the Lord's Paska, for Christ our God has transported us who sing the triumphal hymn from
death to life and from earth.
to heaven. Even though you descended into the grave of a mortal one, you destroyed the power of
Hades, and you arose a victor, O Christ our God, saying to the murder bearing women hail, and to
your apostles granting peace. You also grant resurrection to the fallen. Proclaiming Christ,
victor over sin and death, you're listening to Ancient Faith Radio, your Orthodox Internet radio
connection.
You are listening to Mysterion.
Join Father
Richard Renee, for words homiletical and poetical, reflective and narrative.
Come and explore the challenges of the spiritual life at the intersection of the eternal gospel in the 21st century.
The name of the Father and of the Son is the Holy Spirit. Amen. Christ is risen.
Christ is risen.
Well, I don't know about you, but my lens...
and Holi Week, Pasco, Bright Week, Journey, tends to follow a similar pattern year after year.
I begin lense with a whole host of hopes and expectations.
A basket full of seeds, as it were, overflowing.
By the time that I reach the end of lense, I have supposedly planted those seeds,
but I'm left with not much, a few scraggly little plants.
poking their head up, but mostly weeds.
By the time Holy Week rolls around,
I've usually succeeded in stepping on a few toes
and have mine stepped on a few times also.
And feeling as if I haven't done much with what Lent had to offer.
Then Paska comes and in the brightness of all of that,
of that. I'm able to let go.
of the mediocrity and the failure of Lent for a little while, and Bright Week is very
nice as always. But then as the week's roll by, Pasco
starts to fade into the background. And slowly, but slowly, it returns to business as usual.
Now, that's, I'm speaking for myself here. And if you've had the incredible transformative
experience of Lenton are now glowing with uncreated
light, you can feel free to take an nap during this sermon. But if you have had an experience
anything like mine, then you might be asking yourself, as I am asking myself, how can
this year be different? How can it be different this time around? How can I break through this
time in a way that I have not in all of the lengths and passers.
Past.